<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Amorous convert being a true relation of what happened in Holland.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1679</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 175 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 97 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A25306</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing A3019A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R170298</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12725593</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12725593</idno>
            <idno type="VID">66367</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A25306)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 66367)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 373:10)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The Amorous convert being a true relation of what happened in Holland.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[3], 183 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by R.E. for Richard Tonson ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1679.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"Licensed Octob. 19, 1678. Ro. L'Estrange"</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Greg Schutz</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Greg Schutz</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:66367:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:66367:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE AMOROUS Convert.</p>
            <p>Being a True RELATION Of what happened in <hi>HOLLAND.</hi>
            </p>
            <floatingText type="license" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <p>LICENSED,</p>
                  <closer>
                     <date>Octob. 19. 1678.</date>
                     <signed>Ro. L'Eſtrange.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>R. E.</hi> for <hi>Richard Ton<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon,</hi> within <hi>Grayes-Inne-Gate,</hi> next <hi>Grayes-Inne-Lane.</hi> 1679.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:66367:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:66367:2"/>
            <head>THE AMOROUS Convert.</head>
            <p>ONE of the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi>'s Officers, that, by reaſon of his Poſt and courage, was one of the laſt that endeavoured to ſave himſelf from the fury of the Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, which the People of <hi>Amſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam</hi> had let looſe on their own Amy, had curioſity enough, in the midſt of danger, to take up ſomething that floated by his ſide on the top of the Stream. As ſoon as he had recovered dry ground, he ſaw 'twas a Ball of Wax that ſeem'd to have ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:66367:3"/>in it; and having pull'd it aſunder, he found a Paper with theſe Words written in great Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, <hi>If this Note fall into the Hands of a Gentleman of Merit, I conjure him, in the name of Love and Glory, to come and reſcue a Perſon from miſery, that perhaps he will not think unworthy of a better Fortune.</hi> A little lower in leſs Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racters was added: <hi>If he accept this offer, let him come next</hi> Friday, <hi>at Four of the Clock in the After<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noon, to the Door of the Synagogue of</hi> Amſterdam, <hi>with a green Rib<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band in his Hat.</hi> This was writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten both in <hi>French</hi> and <hi>Low Dutch:</hi> but the Addreſs, to a <hi>Gentleman of Merit,</hi> was very general, for hardly in the whole Army, could it have light upon one that would not have given himſelf that Title; ſo natural is it to Men, if they have really good qualities, to be the firſt in perceiving them, and if they
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:66367:3"/>have not, in uſurping them. But, by good fortune, the direction of this Note was fitted for the Perſon that found it, and it could not eaſily have met in any other, all that which goes to the making a Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lant Man. Though he was ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently uſed to Adventures, yet he was ſurprized with the odneſs of this, the place of Rendezvous, as well as all things elſe, ſeeming ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary. After, having muſed on it a while, he let the Troops paſs, and followed by none but his Man, he took the way to <hi>Mayden,</hi> a little Town three Leagues from <hi>Amſterdam.</hi> The wearineſs of his Journey was not ſufficient to give him a ſound Sleep, which was broke three or four times with the violent working of his Spirits, which were the more inflamed by the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant repreſentation of the ſame Image, Three or Four times one after another. <hi>However it be,</hi> ſaid
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:66367:4"/>he ſtill as he waked, <hi>if ſhe be as fair as ſhe appears in my Dream, I ſhall not repent my pains.</hi> For you muſt know he was only concern'd for her Beauty, making no queſtion of <hi>his own ſucceſs;</hi> for his own nature, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a <hi>Frenchman,</hi> and his good for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune in a great many Intrigues, had given him ſo good an opinion of himſelf, that he doubted not the Lady, whether ſhe were <hi>Dutch</hi> or <hi>French,</hi> would not fail to be equal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly taken with his Wit and good Meen.</p>
            <p>He was of the Family of <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignan,</hi> that is conſiderable enough in <hi>Zaintonge</hi> and <hi>Poictou.</hi> He was known by the name of <hi>Villeneufe,</hi> a ſmall Lordſhip that belonged to the younger Brothers of that Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; the Alliance that he had with the Marqueſs of <hi>Boulaye</hi> had drawn him into the Civil Wars of <hi>France,</hi> where he had behaved him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf very bravely for a Man of two
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:66367:4"/>and twenty. But the Loyalty that was in his nature making him re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent his bearing Arms againſt his own King, after the ſecond Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicades of <hi>Paris,</hi> he retired, with ſome others, firſt to <hi>Bruxells,</hi> and then into <hi>Holland,</hi> that then was called the retreat of brave Men that voluntarily baniſhed them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves their own Country.</p>
            <p>His merit was quickly known, and the Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> who was extreme happy in finding out the good Qualities of worthy Men and generous in rewarding them, gave this Gentleman a Company in the Regiment of <hi>Hautervie.</hi> You need not queſtion, that having ſpent all his Youth in War, he knew not perfectly the Duty and Office of a Souldier; but, beſides that, he had a great facility in ſpeaking Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guages, and writ ſo well in Proſe and Verſe, that a great many Sparks, who take a glory in their
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:66367:5"/>ignorance, found fault with his Learning, and ſaid, he wrote too well for a Gentleman. But the Ladies were not of that Opinion, and there was hardly one of them, either of the Princeſs of <hi>Orange</hi>'s Court, or the Queen of <hi>Bohemia</hi>'s, that would not have paid one of his Letters willingly with one of their own. And indeed he was ſo liberal, diſcreet, and complaiſant, that he could not fail of gaining very much on the Sex. Beſides, his Air, his Shape, and his Hair, which he wore of his own, made a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain mixture that touched at firſt ſight. With all this he had as much courage as he ought, which helpt to bring him off with honour from many an Engagement which his good Meen had occaſioned.</p>
            <p>After a conſiderable ſtay at the <hi>Hague,</hi> he had invitations to go to <hi>Stockholme,</hi> where the Queen of <hi>Suede</hi> was well pleaſed to welcome
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:66367:5"/>Men of his Character; and having reſolv'd to take that Journey with two of his Friends, <hi>La Chaſtre</hi> and <hi>Perſans,</hi> he went to take leave of the Prince, who freely gave it him, only deſiring his company for two or three days, which was when the Army appeared before <hi>Amſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam,</hi> where he met with that ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary Note, in ſo extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary a manner.</p>
            <p>After having paſſed the Night as unquietly as he did, he got up early in the Morning to purſue his Journey to <hi>Amſterdam. But,</hi> ſaid he to himſelf, <hi>why ſo much haſte? Perhaps this Note came only from ſome idle Hand, that had no other de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign than to abuſe him that ſhould find it. And ſhall I not look very ſillily, to make a ſerious buſineſs of anothers Impertinence. But on the other ſide, I have told no body of it, and therefore am in no danger to be laugh'd at. And had I not found
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:66367:6"/>this Note, I muſt have gone to</hi> Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterdam <hi>however, to have found ſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping for</hi> Stockholme.</p>
            <p>And above all, there was a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret force that led him to believe, that ſomething extraordinary and real would arrive to him out of this adventure, and as if he had been already aſſur'd of the truth of his own imaginations, he began ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly to contrive how he ſhould convey a Perſon that Heaven and his own Fancy conſpired to give him. He read the Note again, and ſtaying on theſe words, <hi>Reſcue a Perſon from miſery: Without doubt,</hi> ſays he, <hi>'tis ſome young and rich Woman that is going to be married againſt her will; and that having a noble mind, chooſes rather to marry a Gentleman that ſhe does not know, than ſome poor conditioned Merchant that ſhe does both know, deſpiſe, and hate. Ten thouſand Pound in Gold will do me no great hurt, and may
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:66367:6"/>be eaſily enough convey'd away.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The difference of our Quality ſhall never hinder me from ſo advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tageous a Fortune; and to ſpeak the truth, why ſhould we undervalue Merchants, when all our life is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elſe but a different ſort of Commerce; and we that have No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility ought to truck it with thoſe that have Money, thereby ſupplying each others wants. Is there not enough examples of this at the</hi> Hague, <hi>where</hi> Aumale <hi>has mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried the Daughter of a</hi> Burgomaſter <hi>of</hi> Leyden, Mombas <hi>the Daughter of</hi> Grotius, <hi>and</hi> de Bret <hi>had wit enough to advance his Fortunes the ſame way.</hi> At this rate did he en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertain himſelf, as if the Lady and the Money were both in his hand, and this was the effect of his hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour that never preſented him but with pleaſing Ideas.</p>
            <p>The only thing that troubled him was the place of Aſſignation.
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:66367:7"/>
               <hi>Why before the Door of the Syna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gogue? Is ſhe a</hi> Jew, <hi>if ſhe be, I have done with her, for I have no great fancy for that People.</hi> With theſe ſort of thoughts he came to <hi>Amſterdam,</hi> and lodg'd himſelf in a by Quarter of the Town, to ſhun the meeting with his acquaintance. He had been often in that great City, which is as well worth ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing as any in the World. One may very well ſay that all <hi>Holland</hi> is a Miracle of Art, where nature de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned nothing; and that it has made the refuſe of the Sea more conſiderable, than almoſt all the Land of <hi>Europe.</hi> The wonderful diligence of the People firſt provid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed againſt the power of the Ocean, by ſtupendious works, and then took care to adorn their acquiſition with all the beauties imaginable: For, above Forty Miles together there is nothing to be ſeen but the fineſt Scene in the whole World;
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:66367:7"/>for ſo one may juſtly call all that green Country, filled with Hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, neatly built, and delicately painted.</p>
            <p>I muſt confeſs that <hi>Saumaiſe</hi> made another diſcription of <hi>Holland,</hi> when he ſaid 'twas the Country from whence the four Elements were baniſhed; and where the Idol of Gold, crowned with Tobacco, ſits enthroned upon a Cheeſe. And this unlucky Picture is ſomething like the Original, for in all that Province ſo famous, the Earth brings forth no Fruit, the Water is not to be drunk, and the Air is as thick as Smoak, and as heavy as a Fog, and the Fire ſtinks ſo cruelly, that they are forced to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cloſe it in Stoves. And Cheeſe (mix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with dry Fiſh) is the chiefeſt part of their ſubſiſtence, as Tobacco is of their diverſion: And Gold, which has every where the ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme Authority, did then govern
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:66367:8"/>there ſo abſolutely, that one would have thought <hi>Peru</hi> had there emptied all its Treaſure. Which had, nevertheleſs, its chief Seat at <hi>Amſterdam,</hi> which exceeds all others in Beauty and Pride; and paſſes, according to the judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of beſt Travellers, the Cities of <hi>Italy,</hi> in Circuit, Magnificence, and Regularity. In a word, without mentioning the particular Streets, that by their neatneſs, and uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form proportion, give a ſurprizing pleaſure; one can hardly believe the number and ſplendor of their publick Buildings; among which the State-houſe paſſes for one of the wonders of the World. The very Hoſpitals themſelves, exceeding, in riches and fineſs, the Buildings of moſt other places, of which there are Ten for the ſuccour of ſeveral ſorts of Humane misfortunes, which equally ſhew both Charity and Plenty.</p>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:66367:8"/>
            <p>And to make the wonder the greater, ſeveral ſuch Structures have been the work of private Perſons. Very lately a Merchant that had gain'd, in the <hi>Levant,</hi> a vaſt Eſtate, returning to <hi>Amſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam;</hi> offered two Tun of Gold to found an Hoſpital, to maintain ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral ſort of Animals that could no longer be of any uſe. He had ſeen that extravagant ſort of Charity practiſed among the <hi>Indians,</hi> where almoſt in every Town you ſee a publick Houſe to receive aged Horſes, ſick Dogs, and other ſort of afflicted Animals with a ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular Humanity. Thoſe poor Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple uſe that Hoſpitality out of a Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtition, believing that the Souls of Men paſs into the Bodies of Beaſts, and ſo ſome of them think, that in taking care of a ſick Camel, they may chance to tend their Grandfather. Perhaps our good <hi>Hollander</hi> might have ſome ſuch
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:66367:9"/>fancy in his head, and on that ſcore the Magiſtrates of <hi>Amſterdam</hi> would not admit of ſuch an Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpital.</p>
            <p>There is a thouſand things fit to amuſe Perſons Curioſity, but there is nothing more ſurprizing than that part of the City called, <hi>The Emperour</hi>'s <hi>Canal;</hi> which is thrice as long as that of St. <hi>James</hi>'s <hi>Park.</hi> The Water that runs in the middle is ſo clear, and kept ſo high, that almoſt all day 'tis covered with little Boats painted and gilded, that ſail there for pleaſure, or carriage. There the greateſt heats of the day are never troubleſome, becauſe the rows of great Trees, planted in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der on each ſide, with one half of their Boughs, ſhadow the Canal, and with the other afford a moſt plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing ſhade to the walk on the Key. Theſe Trees as thick and ſhady as they are, do not hinder the Eye from delighting it ſelf with the
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:66367:9"/>magnificence of the Houſes that are built on each ſide of the Canal. In other places, where all things are complemented into fine names, thoſe Houſes ſhould be called Pala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces; which name they better de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve, then moſt Structures that have it. They have not their en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance even with the Street, but by an aſcent of ſeveral ſteps of Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, bordered with a Baluſtrade of Iron guilded. The Eye alone has not its ſatisfaction, but there are Charms proper for the Ear too, an infinity of Birds making a ſweet and natural conſort, from all the boughs of thoſe Trees, that are planted on that lovely Canal.</p>
            <p>If any thing could have divert<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>Villeneuſe</hi> from the entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment his amorous thoughts gave him, it would have been ſo plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing an employment as that of viewing theſe Rarities; but he had his Heart ſo ſet on ſeeing the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:66367:10"/>of his impatience, that he cared for ſeeing nothing elſe.</p>
            <p>At laſt the day of appointment being come, he dreſſed himſelf as well as he could, not forgetting the green Ribband, and walked to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the Synagogue. The Door was open, but as yet he ſaw no Body there, but ſome Men who were ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting up Tents very finely made, that were ranged from the top of the Synagogue to the bottom, almoſt as the Beds of an Hoſpital; as he was looking upon them, one of the Workmen, that lov'd to hear him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf talk, told him that thoſe Tents were ſet up for a Feaſt, which the <hi>Jews</hi> keep every year in the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of <hi>September,</hi> called, <hi>The Feaſt of Tabernacles: The truth is,</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued he, to have the Ceremony exact, <hi>theſe Tents ſhould be ſet up in the Fields, and ſo we obſerve it in</hi> Aſia <hi>and</hi> Africa, <hi>where we are al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed a greater liberty than here,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:66367:10"/>and that is more ſuitable to our de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign, which is to keep in memory the life our Fathers led in the Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſs for forty years together, where they had no Lodging, but a kind of Tabernacles like theſe Tents we now ſet up. But here in</hi> Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rope, <hi>where we do not enjoy ſo much liberty, we cannot perform this ſolemnity with that Purity and State we could wiſh; though we have lately offered a conſiderable ſum to the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates here for obtaining the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty we deſire. The worſt of it is, that being obliged to leave our hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes for a whole week to paſs it here, we are forced to eat, and drink, and ſleep in the ſame place where we aſſemble for our devotions, which is very inconvenient. And muſt all Perſons of each Family be aſſiſtant at this Ceremony,</hi> ſaid Villeneufe. <hi>No, Sir,</hi> ſaid he, <hi>and, we have ordered now, becauſe of the hot weather, and littleneſs of the place, that
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:66367:11"/>there ſhall come but one of a Family:</hi> and having ſaid that the Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny would not begin yet a good while, our Adventurer went a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way full of new hopes. <hi>She'll lye alone,</hi> ſaid he, <hi>and will have much greater freedom this eight days of the Fedst, than ſhe could have at any other time; I ſee ſhe has wit to chuſe her time, and order her deſigns.</hi> With theſe fancies in his head he went away a little longer than he ſhould, for when he came back he ſaw the Ceremony was begun: But he was ſtrangely confounded, when, before the Door of the Syna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gogue, he met two Gentlemen of his own Country and acquaintance, who had been in the Army before <hi>Amſterdam</hi> as well as he, and who he thought had been returned, as the Army was, into the ſeveral Garriſons. They had both more green Ribband than he himſelf, one had nothing elſe but green in
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:66367:11"/>his Hat, and the other had a trim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming all of the ſame eolour. All three fell a laughing at one another, and <hi>Villeneufe</hi> cryed out, <hi>'Tis the ſame deſign that has brought us all hither.</hi> With that the other two confeſſed the truth, and each of them produced their Notes, all writ with the ſame hand, and contain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the very ſame words. <hi>In troth,</hi> ſays Villeneufe, <hi>we may call this fiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for Gallants, for we were all in the Water when we were biting at theſe Notes.</hi> And ſo burſt our a laughing, maintaining however that he was not made ſo great a Fool as they, becauſe he was come to <hi>Amſterdam</hi> to embarque for <hi>Sue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den,</hi> whereas they had come thither only to be laughed at. The truth is, it was pleaſant enough to ſee three <hi>French</hi> Gentlemen all dreſs'd up in green, entertaining themſelves at the Door of a Synagogue with a deſign upon ſome of the Daughters
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:66367:12"/>of <hi>Abraham;</hi> and they were ſo ſenſible themſelves of being expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, that they agreed among them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves never to ſpeak one word of it.</p>
            <p>In the mean time the Ceremony was begun, and being at it, they reſolved to ſatisfie their curioſity and ſee it, before they went to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together. The Women were all on one ſide covered with great Mantles, that hid all their ſhape, and they held in their hand Bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of Trees, as well as the Men, who were placed over againſt them; ſo that all the place was full of green, which made ſome myſtery in their Religion. <hi>For ought I ſee,</hi> ſays one of our Sparks, <hi>green makes a piece of the Ceremony, and when we were ordered to put it in our Hats, we were treated like Proſelyte Jews.</hi> Whiles he was talking, <hi>Villeneufe,</hi> who ſtill had a ſtrong fancy of ſome real adven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:66367:12"/>turned his Eyes on all ſides; and he perceived a Woman, cover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with her Mantle, left her place, and, with a languiſhing Air, went into one of the Tents, where ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Woman followed her; but he had not obſerved that the other, which was her Woman, had before ſoftly pulled her by the Mantle, which had made her counterfeit a little indiſpoſition to leave her place. <hi>Madam,</hi> ſays ſhe, <hi>there are Three with green Ribband, and therefore I thought fit to ask you what I ſhould do.</hi> The Lady having thought a little, at laſt took the end of a piece of Parchment, that was interwoven up and down on her Garments, according to the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Cuſtome, and after having done ſomething with a little Bod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kin ſhe pulled out of her Head, <hi>Here,</hi> ſays ſhe, <hi>give this to one of them ſo neatly, that the others may not ſee you. But to which of them,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:66367:13"/>Madam? To him that has the beſt Meen,</hi> ſays ſhe; <hi>But becauſe thy judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, it may be, will be different from mine, go about them, and having well marked them, bring me word what thou thinkeſt of them.</hi> She came back preſently, and told her, <hi>Oh, Madam, one cannot miſtake: There is one ſo extraordinary, who is as handſome for a Man, as you are for a Woman. Perhaps for all that,</hi> ſaid ſhe laughing, <hi>you may be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived, for there be a many of thoſe handſome Men, who are great Cheats.</hi> However, they reſolved the hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomeſt ſhould have it, which the good Woman could not have ſo well executed, if <hi>Villeneufe</hi> had not plaid his part. For ſeeing the Woman fig'd about as ſhe did, he imagined there was ſomething in the Wind, and as ſhe came by him, he let fall his Handkerchief, which ſhe took up and gave him with a great deal of civility.</p>
            <pb n="23" facs="tcp:66367:13"/>
            <p>The Ceremony laſted not long, for it conſiſted chiefly in bowing of themſelves towards the Eaſt, where <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> is ſcituated, and in ſinging the 113. <hi>Pſalm,</hi> waving up and down the Branches they held in their Hands. After the Ceremony was over, the Three Cavaliers paſſed the Evening to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, though <hi>Villeneuf</hi> was impa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient till he had ſeen what 'twas that he thought he felt in his Hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kerchief: 'Twas very late before he could ſatisfie his curioſity, and at laſt he found 'twas a bit of Parch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; where he ſaw nothing but Characters that he did not under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand, that were writ on the ſides of it. <hi>They laugh at me,</hi> ſays he, flinging down his Parchment, <hi>to write me Love Letters in Hebrew: do I look ſo like a Rabbin, that they think I underſtand their Language?</hi> However, being loath to give o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver his hopes, he fancied there was
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:66367:14"/>ſome miſtake, and that he ſhould ſee more of it the next day.</p>
            <p>To conſider the matter right, one could not judge very well of a Note ſent ſo uncertain a way, and of ſo odd a kind, of an aſſignation given at the Door of the Syna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gogue, and of a concern that made an interruption in the ſolemneſt act of Divine Worſhip. There was in all this a certain Air of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trigue, and Face of Gallantry, on which the greateſt goodneſs in the World could not put a favourable conſtruction. But appearances are falſe, as they were here, where all this idle and vain romantick ſhew did cover a very good intention, and a very laudible deſign.</p>
            <p>The Night being ſpent, <hi>Ville<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neufe</hi> again looked on his Parch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; and all the while his Man was dreſſing him, did nothing but turn it up and down, and at laſt perceived ſome Letters marked
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:66367:14"/>without Ink on the ſide where nothing was writ, <hi>To Morrow at the ſame hour again. With all my heart,</hi> ſays he, <hi>though there were a thouſand dangers in the way. Dumaieſt,</hi> ſaid he to his Man, <hi>thou laugheſt, but for all that, here is a buſineſs will ſtop our Journey to</hi> Sueden. For he no longer doubted, but in the progreſs of ſuch an Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venture, he ſhould find engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments ſufficient to detain him. And being in this mind, he wrote to his Friends, <hi>La Chaſtre</hi> and <hi>Perſans,</hi> to execuſe himſelf from going with them, as he had promiſed, to <hi>Stock<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holm,</hi> without giving them any account of the true reaſon of his ſtay. After having ſent away theſe Letters, he made haſte to his aſſignation the ſecond time, where he found the Bearer of the Parch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, who, without looking on him, bid him follow her at a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, and go into the houſe after
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:66367:15"/>her. He obeyed exactly, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, having paſſed ſeveral Streets, he ſaw his Guide open a little Door; he went in after her, into a little Room, pretty neat; where he found himſelf alone with a Woman who was about Five and Fifty, dreſſed like a Citizens Wife. <hi>Here, Sir,</hi> ſaid ſhe, <hi>is a glorious For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune, enough to make the Paradiſe of a Prince. I am much obliged to you,</hi> ſaid Villeneuſe, <hi>but when ſhall I know the Perſon that is to make my happineſs. There is time enough for that,</hi> ſaid ſhe, <hi>and in the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the Night—What do you mean,</hi> ſays he, <hi>by the beginning of the Night, 'tis now but four of the Clock; if you make me ſtay ſo long, you'll find me dead. We'll pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent that, I warrant you,</hi> ſays ſhe, laughing, <hi>here is Wine, and Sweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meats, and if you have a mind to read, there are Books for you, for I provided for you, that you might
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:66367:15"/>not be tired with being alone.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Villeneufe</hi> ſeeing her gone, <hi>What a do is here,</hi> ſaid he? <hi>what is this to raiſe my deſires by greater expecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion?</hi> Then looking on the Bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tles of Wine, <hi>I am treated here right according to the cuſtom of the Country; imagining I cannot be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſie, as long as I have the Bottle by me.</hi> Then looking upon the Books, he found they were the Tomes of <hi>Aſtrea</hi> and <hi>Polexandre,</hi> and that on the firſt Leaves there was writ, <hi>Joſebeth.</hi> With that he aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſur'd himſelf he had found the name of his Miſtreſs. <hi>Theſe Books,</hi> ſaid he, <hi>are not very proper for an old Woman; They are</hi> Joſebeth's, ſaid he, <hi>and 'tis like the name of a Maid, as I wiſhed in my ſoul ſhe would be.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now the Night came on, and there being no Moon, it was extreme dark, the only thing that could draw <hi>Villeneufe</hi> from his ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litude.
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:66367:16"/>His Guide then being come to take him, ſhe carried him three or four Houſes farther, where they found a back door open, which let them into a little Garden, out of which our <hi>Frenchman</hi> was led into an Apartment where he was locked in. The Cieling, that was richly gilt, made it ſelf be ſeen in the Floor; which being paved with poliſhed Marble in Squares, of black and white, ſhined all over like a Glaſs, except in that part where there was a <hi>Turky</hi> Carpet laid under a little Summer Bed of green Sattin, lightly embroidered with Silver, with a Furniture of the ſame, rich enough for the Seaſon. There it was that <hi>Villeneufe,</hi> as ſtout as he was, began to have his Heart beat; and though he had paſſed dangers enough in his life, in none of them had he ever felt ſuch emotions as he did now. And he had reaſonenough, for never did there any thing pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:66367:16"/>it ſelf to his Eyes, that ſtruck them and his Heart ſo much, as a Perſon that he ſaw enter the Room at a Door over againſt him. She had on a Simarr of Cloth of Gold, tucked up on each ſide with a great bunch of Cherry-colour Ribband, and under it a Petticoat of ſo fine a gare, that diſcovered all the ſhape of her Legs and Knees: About her Neck another ſort of light gare folded together like the <hi>Vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tian</hi> Women, that hung over her Breaſt, but left open its gentle ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing as ſhe breathed, enough to have kindled flame in a <hi>Stoick:</hi> Behind her Head, her Hair bound up with Pearl in great foldings, and fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling down on the ſides in curls, of the lovelieſt black in the World, which yet was not neceſſary to ſet off her complexion; the whiteneſs of her Skin being of a kind to dazle any Eye that beheld it.</p>
            <p>Her Eyes alone, without any
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:66367:17"/>other help, had but too much power to dazle an Admirer; for they had ſo much Fire, but ſo ſoft and gentle a Fire, that with the briskneſs of black Eyes, for ſo they were, there ſparkled too <hi>all</hi> that which the gray Eyes uſe to have, that's tender and moving. You may beſt gueſs what <hi>Joſebeth</hi> was, when all the Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men that ſaw and envyed her Beauty, yet could find no fault in it, but that her mouth was rather too wide; but that fault was very neceſſary, becauſe without it, one could not have ſeen the delicateſt Teeth that ever were. With all this, a certain air of youth, that hung about her, and a way and port that would have covered any faults her Perſon could have had, rendred her a moſt accompliſhed Creature. And this <hi>Villeneufe</hi> found by experience to be true, for at the inſtant that he ſaw her, he ran to fling himſelf at her Feet,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:66367:17"/>without being able to ſay one word, but, <hi>Oh Madam;</hi> which he repeat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed two or three times like a Man poſſeſſed, and ſo ſtaid a great while with his mouth faſtned on her hand, which the beautiful Viſion had reached out to take him up. <hi>Something muſt be allowed,</hi> ſaid ſhe, ſmiling, <hi>for the tranſports of a ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſe, but you muſt not expect to be uſed always at this rate:</hi> And then having obliged him to riſe, they began a Converſation ſo full of wit, and to have a reciprocal e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteem ſo great, as made them wiſh they two had only been made for one another.</p>
            <p>The meeting of an inclination ſo ſtrong and ſudden; kept them not from having a Quarrel in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of their acquaintance: For <hi>Villeneufe,</hi> either willing to ſhew his wit, or elſe out of a braver concern which a ſtrong paſſion does often raiſe, looking very
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:66367:18"/>gravely, <hi>And what, Madam, will you ſay, if the firſt time I ſee you, I ſhould take the confidence to pick a quarrel with you, with good appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of reaſon? I ſhould ſay,</hi> an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered ſhe diſdainfully, and pulling back her Hand, <hi>that you were very ungrateful, and gathering from thence a belief of your ill nature and ingratitude for any further favour I might ſhew you, 'tis very likely I ſhould preſently put an end to our ſtory.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>But, Madam, ſuppoſe my com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint ſhould only come from an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs of eſteem? You might then make it,</hi> ſaid ſhe, <hi>with a great deal of aſſurance, and pray let us know what it is.</hi> Thereupon he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed he was really vexed ſhe had ſent ſo many ſeveral Notes a ſwim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming, conſidering that thereby he had been in danger to have loſt her; if any other that had found them, had had better fortune than
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:66367:18"/>he in coming firſt to the Door of the Synagogue. <hi>Truly,</hi> ſays ſhe, <hi>you are very pleaſant, and how ſhould I have ſent out one to you, whom I never ſaw? but me thinks you ſhould rather be pleaſed with the ſucceſs, which has given me occaſion to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer you by my own choice to two o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers that had the ſame fortune at firſt with your ſelf; and therefore I must come back to my firſt opinion, that you are a little apt to be ungrate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful. Villeneufe</hi> had not great diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty to appeaſe this little anger, and afterwards asked of her with great paſſion, what he ſhould do to make her happineſs, as ſhe had in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timated in her Note. <hi>You are little too haſty,</hi> ſaid <hi>Joſebeth</hi> bluſhing, <hi>we do not yet know one another enough to explain that myſtery. Ah, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam,</hi> ſays he, quite tranſported, <hi>I do not ſo much as know whether you are already in the power of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Man? Solomoune,</hi> ſaid ſhe, <hi>that
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:66367:19"/>brought you hither, will inform you of my concerns; take notice of her Houſe, and come thither</hi> Monday <hi>towards the Evening, where ſhe will fully instruct you, and afterwards bring you hither in the beginning of the Night. Villeneufe</hi> again threw himſelf at her feet, and <hi>Joſebeth</hi> holding down her head to take him up, inclined it a little towards his, with which he was ſo tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſported, that he cryed out, <hi>Oh, why does not all the world know my good Fortune; and why may not I cry out, I have ſeen her, I have ſeen her, I have ſeen her. No more of this,</hi> ſaid ſhe, a little troubled, and very ſerious, <hi>though you are a</hi> French<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, <hi>remember you are not in</hi> France, <hi>and therefore pray no cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out of your Victory.</hi> That little heat of joy ſcaped from <hi>Villeneufe</hi> againſt his will, and without de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign; for though he was a <hi>French<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man,</hi> yet in that he differed from
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:66367:19"/>moſt of his Nation, being moſt perfectly diſcreet; and thence he took occaſion to make a thouſand Vows both of his Secreſie and Faith; to which ſhe gave a rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy belief, becauſe ſhe had no mind to doubt them. As he was going away, he would have left ſome Tokens of his liberality with <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomoune,</hi> but ſhe refuſed them with ſome kind of diſdain. Though it were a good way from thence to his own Lodging, yet he was at home before he thought of it; ſo much was he taken up with his own Reflections, among which he had ſome that he could not well re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>concile. He ſaw plainly enough that <hi>Joſebeth</hi> was married, and that being, he could not compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend how ſhe had put honour into her Note ſhe had ſent upon the Water. On the other ſide, if it were only an amorous Intrigue, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out other deſign than that of plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:66367:20"/>why had ſhe not made uſe of the firſt occaſion that was ſo fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vourable to ſatisfie it.</p>
            <p>To think ſhe was in a confuſion, becauſe of the odneſs and newneſs of the Adventure, was ridiculous, for 'twas an appointment of her own making, and of which ſhe was abſolutely the Miſtreſs. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>midſt all theſe doubts there was one thing ſure enough, and that was the merit of <hi>Joſebeth;</hi> which he preferred to all that ever he had known, even to young <hi>Riparda,</hi> that was then the handſomeſt Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon at the <hi>Hague,</hi> and now is Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſs of <hi>Caravas.</hi> Being ſo taken with the Qualities of the lovely <hi>Joſebeth,</hi> he expected impatiently to have a full account of all her concerns; and being come to his Lodgings, he made a reſolution, which he had never done before, to go through all difficulties for the obtaining of <hi>Joſebeth.</hi> Who, for her part, was as much pleaſed
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:66367:20"/>with him, as he could be with her. <hi>Fortune,</hi> ſaid ſhe, <hi>has done more for me than Wiſdom;</hi> and thereupon ſhe applauded her own fancy, which gave her more ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction in one hour, than all the wiſe counſels of her Friends had given her in all her life: The only trouble ſhe had, was cauſed by her fear that <hi>Villeneufe,</hi> for whom ſhe already had felt ſo great a kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, might abate in the eagerneſs of his deſires, when he came to know her ſtory: <hi>But, ſure that can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be,</hi> ſaid ſhe, <hi>he appears generous, and there is nothing in my ſtory, that can occaſion any thing but pity.</hi> So that ſhe would not recall the orders ſhe had given <hi>Solomoun</hi> to tell her life to <hi>Villeneufe.</hi> Who being ready at the hour appointed: <hi>You ſhall know all our Affairs,</hi> ſaid ſhe, <hi>and judge by that if we have a Friendſhip for you or no. Our Miſtreſs,</hi> being you will have it ſo, <hi>was born at</hi> Metz <hi>in</hi> Lorraine, <hi>two and twenty years ago; her Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:66367:21"/>was one of the richeſt Men of that City, and of that ſort that live upon the income of their Rents. Though he made an outward profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of Chriſtianity, yet in his heart he was a</hi> Jew, <hi>being deſcended of the Tribe of</hi> Benjamin, <hi>as well as his Wife. She left him Widdower when he was but young, without any Child but the little</hi> Joſebeth, <hi>who, though ſhe were but ſix years old, was admired by all the World. I had been her Nurſe, and her Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther was pleaſed to truſt me ſo far as to make me her Governeſs, and to take the care of his Houſe, to which I agreed, againſt the advice of my Friends, that I might be near a Child for whom I had ſo great a love. She paſſed for a</hi> Chriſtian, <hi>as well as her Father, and the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to colour the buſineſs, ſhe was called</hi> Mary, <hi>and not</hi> Joſebeth, <hi>which was the name her Mother had ordered ſhould be given her when ſhe was grown up. She had
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:66367:21"/>not been taught any thing of</hi> Jewiſh <hi>Religion; in which I durſt not inſtruct her, for fear, leſt the innocence and ſimplicity of a Child might reveal the ſecret of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily, which was extremely zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous for the Law of</hi> Moſes. <hi>It had been conſiderable at</hi> Rome, <hi>and choſe rather to leave that City, than either to go to Maſs, or elſe to wear a Hat covered with Yellow, as</hi> Paul <hi>the Fourth ordained all thoſe of our Religion ſhould do, both as a diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction and a diſgrace. The zeal of the Family was not at all diminiſhed in our Maſter, who forbare to give his Daughter a</hi> Jewiſh <hi>Education, only out of a belief he had, that a Husband of his own Religion would eaſily bring her back to it. In the mean time the poor man found him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf decay every day, and therefore was very ſolicitous to provide a Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band for his Daughter, leſt his death might prevent the deſign he
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:66367:22"/>had of marrying her to a</hi> Jew. <hi>He wrote therefore to a Friend of his own Tribe at</hi> Amſterdam, <hi>offering him his Daughter and twenty thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand Pounds for her Portion. The young</hi> Jewiſh Hollander <hi>came a wooing, the Match was concluded, and</hi> Joſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth <hi>married before ſhe was full fif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teen years old. Within three Months the Father dyed, and we left</hi> Metz <hi>to come hither.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And here the good Nurſe ſtood ſtill to cry, and <hi>Ville neufe</hi> took that occaſion to ask her wherein was the unhappineſs of <hi>Joſebeth: Has ſhe an ill Husband, does he not uſe her well?</hi> But <hi>Solomoune,</hi> who had no mind to have her diſcourſe broke off, preſently wiped her Eyes, and thus continued it. <hi>Her Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band, whoſe name is</hi> Wanbergue, <hi>denyes her nothing, is handſome, is not above thirty years old, and has a very great Fortune, being one of thoſe rich Merchants who are
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:66367:22"/>more conſiderable than Lords, and ſend little Fleets to trade on their own account. His Father, with a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother Merchant, undertook to make War with a King; let me ſee, I think it was the King of</hi> Denmark, <hi>about the Intereſt of Trade, and would have carried it on themſelves, had not the States forbid them. The Son is as rich as the Father, and you may ſee that he denies his Wife nothing, nothing that ſhe can have either for her own Perſon, or the fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhing her Houſe. Has ſhe no Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lant,</hi> ſaid <hi>Villeneufe. None,</hi> ſaid the Nurſe, <hi>and for ſeven years that we have been in this City, I do not think ſhe has ſpoke four times to any one Man, except it be</hi> Rabby Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſſas. <hi>'Tis not that her Husband is jealous, neither indeed has he the leaſt cauſe; but ſhe has particular reaſons that keep her from entering into any amorous Engagements. And what are thoſe,</hi> ſays our Hero, a
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:66367:23"/>little quicker than before? <hi>'Tis in reſpect of the</hi> Jews, <hi>for whom</hi> Joſebeth <hi>has an invincible averſion, which I think ſhe took in her firſt E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducation. And for the</hi> Chriſtians, <hi>they are all here given to drink, and when they have took a Cup, they tell all they know, and more too.</hi> But af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter all, <hi>My dear Friend,</hi> ſaid <hi>Ville<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neufe</hi> in a cajoling way, <hi>let us come to the point, that I may know wherein conſiſts the misfortune of lovely</hi> Joſebeth, <hi>and wherein I may ſerve her.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>For that,</hi> ſays <hi>Solomoune, I know nothing; neither have I any com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion to ſay any more.</hi> In hopes to draw out the reſt, he looked very kindly upon her, and ſtole into her hand a piece of Gold, to the value of ten Pound; but 'twas in vain, for he could get nothing out of her, but praiſes of her Miſtreſſes wit and ſweet nature. This diſcourſe raiſed in <hi>Villeneufe</hi> a
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:66367:23"/>great eſteem for his Miſtreſs, for he could not but think ſhe was a Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man of extraordinary merit, being her Servant ſaid nothing to her diſadvantage. The truth is, ſhe had ordered her Nurſe to ſay no more, and had kept to her ſelf her own deſign in reſerve, to ſee if <hi>Villeneufe</hi> ſhould deſerve a greater confidence. But 'tis alſo true, that the Nurſe had left out a great part of <hi>Joſebeth</hi>'s Character, which was too delicate for ſuch a Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man to diſtinguiſh. And that was a ſtrange fancy for Romances, which had made extraordinary im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions upon her, from her very Child-hood.</p>
            <p>Another ſort of Man, than her Husband, would eaſily have cured her of this Childiſhneſs, which filled her ſo much with the humour of Adventures, and the pleaſure of extraordinary accidents, that ſhe uſed to ſay, there was nothing ſo
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:66367:24"/>dull as a plain life, without the mix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of ſomething ſingular to em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>belliſh it. And this conceit would ſometimes be ſo ſtrong, that when ſhe conſidered the heavy City-life ſhe led, ſhe was ready to ſeek ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to divert her. <hi>What a wretch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed thing is it,</hi> would ſhe ſay, <hi>to do and ſee the ſame things for a year together, from morning to night the ſame courſe, ſo one a hundred Mile off, might know every hour in the day what I am doing. This is to be buried alive.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>All People have ſome weakneſs, or other, and this was <hi>Joſebeth</hi>'s; but there are few Women that have in recompence ſo many other good qualities as ſhe had. Her youth contributed to the keeping up this humour, as well as that dull life ſhe lead; but this fault was not without cure, and had Heaven bleſſed her in a ſuitable Husband, it would have ſetled her Mind, and
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:66367:24"/>made her one of the fineſt Women in the World. Being of this hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour, it was impoſſible that ſhe ſhould not come to have a great in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>difference for her Husband; and he on his ſide was very well pleaſed with any thing that kept him from paying the marks of his kindneſs to ſuch a Wife: So that by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees, ſhe came almoſt to an intire liberty and diſpoſal of her ſelf; which yet only conſiſted in lying alone, and in having what Cloaths and Furniture ſhe had a mind to: For in all things elſe, <hi>Joſebeth</hi> lived with the ſame diſcretion as the other <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Women do: She never went abroad, but her Face was covered: When <hi>Wanbergue</hi> had Company at home, ſhe never appeared; and no Man, but <hi>Manaſſas,</hi> was permitted to come into her Apartment. And in this ſhe was ſo exact, that though <hi>Aunibal Seſtede,</hi> the <hi>Daniſh</hi> Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadour, did what he could, in a
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:66367:25"/>viſit he made to <hi>Wanbergue,</hi> about the State of Trade, to ſee her, it was to no purpoſe. This way of living infinitely pleaſed <hi>Ville neufe,</hi> to ſee himſelf enjoy a happineſs that other Men only wiſhed for; and for which he was ſo impatient, that he preſſed <hi>Solomoune</hi> to conduct him to <hi>Joſebeth</hi> without any delay. He found that charming Woman ſitting upon a Bed of green Vel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vet, and though the Wax-lights, that were at the other end of the Room, ſent but a little light to that ſide, yet he plainly ſaw that ſhe looked better, and was better dreſſed, than the firſt time that he ſaw her. <hi>Well, Sir,</hi> ſaid ſhe, giv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him a Chair to ſit down, <hi>have you the ſame thoughts of poor</hi> Joſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth, <hi>now that you know her Story, which you had before?</hi> To which queſtion he only anſwered with new adorations; and then added, Solomoune <hi>has left out, Madam, an
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:66367:25"/>eſſential part of your ſtory, and that is, wherein you were unhappy; and to learn it ſhe has ſent me back to you. The truth is,</hi> ſaid ſhe very ſeriouſly, and with a deep ſigh, <hi>that is a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret which I have kept for my ſelf, and I pray God I may find that you deſerve to be truſted with it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Our lovely <hi>Joſebeth,</hi> that with a Childiſhneſs endeavour'd to ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfie her Romantick humour in any thing that did not appear to the World, had put on that day fine Buskins after the old <hi>Roman</hi> way, that ſo upon occaſion ſhe might in part of her dreſſing appear like ſome of the <hi>Heroines.</hi> They were made of <hi>Spaniſh</hi> perfumed Leather, of Musk-colour, cut up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Gold, laced up half way her Leg with Scarlet Ribband, which made ſeveral knots above the ſmall of her Leg, where a Silk Stocking of the ſame colour began to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear. When <hi>Villeneufe</hi> ſaw that
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:66367:26"/>antick fancy, he could not forbear laughing; with which <hi>Joſebeth</hi> was ſo offended, that riſing briskly off the Bed, ſhe ſaid to him, <hi>Oh, Sir, do you laugh, you are very far from what you think, I aſſure you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Villeneufe</hi> was almoſt mad at this unlucky accident, and did all he could to bring her back from a Chair where ſhe ſate very angry. He threw himſelf at her Feet, to ſwear he only laughed out of the joy he had, to ſee his happineſs ſo far advanced. <hi>Juſt ſo I thought,</hi> ſaid ſhe, <hi>and it ſufficiently vexes me to find the Man, that I thought Fate had ſent me on purpoſe, ſhould be juſt like other Men, who, for all their Gallantry, do in their hearts laugh at the Women who have folly enough to ſhew them favour.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Madam,</hi> ſays he, <hi>for Heavens ſake be ſo juſt, as to make a difference betwixt me and thoſe Monſters,
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:66367:26"/>and attribute my mirth only to the thoughts of my pleaſure. 'Tis too much gayety,</hi> ſaid Joſebeth, <hi>and in an affair of that conſequence, ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs looks a great deal better.</hi> With much ado he appeaſed her, ſo that at laſt ſhe told him, playing with his Hair: <hi>I confeſs, I am ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treme unfortunate, and you may make my happineſs, but then it muſt only be in the ways of Honour.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The ways of Honour, Madam! why, what does that mean, you are in the power of another Man, who in all likelyhood will live as long as I. I know very well what I ſay,</hi> ſays Joſebeth, <hi>and that I may be yours, without wronging my Conſcience, by an eaſie and handſome way, which I will tell you, if I find that you are worthy of my Love. In a word, 'tis only in proſpect of this deſign, I ran the venture of that Note which brought you hither, and do not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive your ſelf with any other ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gination.</hi>
               <pb n="50" facs="tcp:66367:27"/>Our <hi>Frenchman</hi> ſaw himſelf cruelly diſappointed of his hopes, and thought himſelf the only unfortunate Man, to whom ever happened ſuch an odd adven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</p>
            <p>On the other ſide, the force and ſolidity of <hi>Joſebeth</hi>'s Reaſon ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared more and more; and tak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing our melancholly Lover by the Hand; <hi>We will love one another,</hi> ſaid ſhe; <hi>eternally, and 'tis for that end that I will never grant you any thing that ſhall hinder us from ſo doing.</hi> At that word <hi>Villeneufe</hi> ſwore a thouſand Oaths, that the goodneſs ſhe ſhould ſhew could ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver hinder him from loving her for ever; but on the contrary would enflame him more, by adding gratitude to love. <hi>No, no,</hi> ſaid ſhe, <hi>you deceive your ſelf; but were it true, that you ſhould afterwards love me the more, you would only thereby be the more miſerable, for I
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:66367:27"/>ſhould hate the ſight of you, and fly from you like Death. Oh, Madam,</hi> ſaid Villeneufe, <hi>what reaſon could you have to uſe me ſo cruelly, after having uſed me ſo kindly. Any Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, of Wit and Honour, would do ſo as well as I; having a horror for thoſe Lovers who make them reflect on their own ſhame. For you muſt know to what exceſs of Love ſoever a Woman may be carried, ſhe ſtill would keep her reputation; and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny times ſuch a Woman may ſhew greater concern for it than another; ſo that as often as ſhe calls to mind, that in the World there is a Man that can reproach her with ſuch a failing, ſhe cannot think of him but with confuſion; but would with all her heart ſee the only witneſs of her ſhame deſtroyed, that ſo ſhe might remain the ſole poſſeſſor of a ſecret, which, if it were poſſible, ſhe would not know her ſelf.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There was ſo much Reaſon,
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:66367:28"/>Senſe, and Honour in what <hi>Joſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth</hi> ſaid, that <hi>Villeneufe</hi> had no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to reply, and yet he could not chuſe but complain, though he confeſſed it was to complain of Reaſon it ſelf. Whereupon the lovely <hi>Joſebeth,</hi> ſmiling upon him, and believing that in his heart he did her juſtice, told him, <hi>I find you now ſo reaſonable, that from this minute I take you into my ſervice, and as I am very juſt in my nature, you need not fear being turned off. And to ſhew you that I will allow you all that I can in decency, I will not go to morrow Night to the Tents of the Synagogue, though my Husband has deſired me to paſs one Night there as well as the reſt, but will let him go alone that I may have the more liberty to entertain you here, on condition that you do not demand any thing which I cannot grant.</hi> And with this precaution ſhe thought ſhe might permit a great
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:66367:28"/>many things to <hi>Villeneufe</hi> innocent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly enough; which ſhe the rather did, becauſe the deſign ſhe had was very juſt; and to carry it on, it was neceſſary to ſee him often, that ſhe might the better know him. <hi>But, Madam,</hi> ſaid he, <hi>if you muſt go paſs a Night at the Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagogue, your Husband muſt then go with you. No,</hi> ſays ſhe, <hi>he durſt not though he had never ſo great a mind to it, for 'tis not lawful for the</hi> Jews <hi>to be with their Wives theſe eight days. If it be ſo, Madam, what ſhould hinder me from waiting on you thither, dreſſed up like a Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, it will be ſome kind of diver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, and you must have ſome body there to wait on you. Nay, if that were,</hi> ſaid ſhe, <hi>I muſt have two, for I cannot be without</hi> Solomoune. So 'twas agreed, to the ſatisfaction of <hi>Joſebeth,</hi> that was pleaſed with the novelty, to think, that never before was there any one ſo attend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:66367:29"/>to celebrate the Feaſt of Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bernacles. By this you may ſee what was the humour of <hi>Joſebeth,</hi> and therein ſhe did not much differ from other Women, whoſe Ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is much greater than the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority they are allowed. They have ſo good an Opinion of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, that they would, if they could, manage the moſt important Affairs of State: And ſeeing that Pleaſure is denyed them, they are deſirous to ſhew their power in leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer concerns, and think they have done pretty well, if they are the occaſion of any thing extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary.</p>
            <p>But this deſign of <hi>Villeneufe</hi> was eaſie to execute; he was ſlen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der enough in the Waſte to paſs for a Maid, eſpecially in that Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, where Men are not of the moſt delicate ſhape; and he knew the better, the way and carriage of a Woman, having formerly in a Bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>let
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:66367:29"/>at the <hi>Hague,</hi> been dreſſed up for the part of a <hi>Sultan,</hi> which he performed very well: So that he reſolved to go to <hi>Solomoune</hi>'s, and take the Cloaths his Miſtreſs would ſend him. However, when he was alone, he did a little blame ſo extravagant a Gallantry, and made ſuch reflections, as ſome Men, eſpecially thoſe of his own Nation, uſe to do when they ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain any thing eaſily, that they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire ardently. Had he known <hi>Joſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth</hi> better, be would not have en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertained ſuch thoughts. But not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding he came to <hi>Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moune</hi>'s, where he found the Cloaths very fit for him, and the old Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man ſo pleaſed in putting them on, as was a little troubleſome. At laſt they both went to their Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſs, and from thence all three towards the Synagogue, where they were no ſooner entred, but the Rabbin, according to the Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome,
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:66367:30"/>made faſt the Doors. It had no light but what came from ten Lamps, hung at an equal diſtance in the Iſle that was betwixt the two rows of Tents; ſo that thoſe who paſſed the Night there could uſe no other light but that which a little melancholy Lamp gave them; and without opening the Door of the Tent they were quite in the dark: <hi>Joſebeth</hi> and her little Train had no great occaſion for light, which occaſioned a little diſpute, for as <hi>Villeneufe</hi> would fain have opened the Door a little to let in ſome light that he might ſee his Miſtreſs, ſhe grew very angry, and thought he ought to be ſatisfied with the liberty he had, and be quiet; <hi>How now,</hi> ſays ſhe, <hi>in the condition we are in, you can go a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout to ask more than you already have? Yes, Madam,</hi> ſaid he, <hi>if I did not deſire more than I have, I ſhould be very ridiculous, for as yet I
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:66367:30"/>have nothing.</hi> He was going on, when there was a great noiſe that ſufficiently frighted them; for it appeared only to be raiſed on their account. For about Midnight all the Synagogue was alarmed with a confuſed cry; and at laſt they learnt the cauſe, that a <hi>Chriſtian,</hi> in Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans Cloaths, was got into the Synagogue, on ſome ill deſign, which made them all cry out, and that they ſhould be revenged on ſuch an impious Wretch.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>We are found out,</hi> ſaid Joſebeth, <hi>and I am ſerved well enough for being ſo impudent.</hi> At which <hi>Vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leneufe</hi> reſolved to leave her Tent, to ſave her from any trouble; and to anſwer to all their queſtions, that curoſity only had brought him thither, and if that would not ſerve, to force his way with a good Piſtol he had under his Coat; im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately he went out, the noiſe increaſing more and more, and
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:66367:31"/>leaving <hi>Joſebeth</hi>'s Tent, he ſtole a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long and got into another Tent on the other ſide, which had the Door half open. He was ſurprized to find a light there, expreſly againſt the orders of the Ceremony, which was in a Dark Lanthorn that one could open or ſhut as one plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes. By this glimmering light he ſaw ſome Papers on the Table, that he took up, I know not why, and having blown out the Candle that was in the Lanthorn, he ſtept aſide; and all this in ſo lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle time, that he eaſily got out be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Perſon to whom the Tent belonged, (and was gone out to ſee what the noiſe meant,) could be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned.</p>
            <p>In the mean time the Tumult was over, and our <hi>Frenchman,</hi> hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing learnt they had found out the Author of that trouble, took heart and went back to <hi>Joſebeth</hi>'s Tent, that was the ninth from the Door.
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:66367:31"/>
               <hi>We are more happy than we deſerve,</hi> ſaid ſhe, ſoftly in his Ear, <hi>for this noiſe was not made for us. A poor wretch, that formerly was of our Religion, got in, in Womens Cloaths, on pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe to ſteal ſome of the Veſſels of Sil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver that we uſe for Incenſe, and 'twas that which gave us the Alarm. Though he and I both diſguiſed our ſelves to get in,</hi> ſaid Villeneufe, <hi>yet the Thefts we intended to make were very different. All that you ſhall rob me off will be my Sleep,</hi> ſaid Joſebeth, <hi>and to confeſs the truth, I am deſperately diſquieted to ſee you here; for the time to come, pray leave me the appointment of our Rendezvous, for the firſt that you have made you ſee is very unlucky.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The truth is, <hi>Joſebeth</hi> was very indiſcreet, with all her wit, to ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture her ſelf at that rate in a place which was perfectly at the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of a Man that hated her mortally. That Man, who was
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:66367:32"/>then infinitely eſteemed of all the <hi>Jews,</hi> and had the chief Anthori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in the Synagogue, was called <hi>Manaſſes Ben Iſrael.</hi> Though he were threeſcore years old, yet he was reckoned a very handſome Man; and for his Wit, he had too much to be beloved, but that he joyned to it a certain taking way, that obliged all the World. Above all, the extraordinary life he had hitherto lead, with the reputation of great Virtue, and without mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rying, as the other Rabbins did, gave him a great Opinion, both a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the <hi>Jews,</hi> and the ſeveral Sects of <hi>Chriſtians</hi> that live at <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterdam.</hi> But this good Opinion was ill placed; for as Hypocriſie is the general dreſs of the World, ſo was it put on by <hi>Manaſſes,</hi> who was one of thoſe, that by appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to have ſome good, are more capable of doing ill. The Gift he had to pleaſe all People and to vex
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:66367:32"/>no body, was a Charm to blind the Eyes of all thoſe that ſaw his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation, without which they would have quickly found a great many things that would have in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced them to believe ill of him in greater matters. That general blind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs had given leave to the Rabbin to enjoy a moſt delicious life for many years, and a very great reputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion at the ſame time. But at laſt the time came when he ſhould be ſeen without a Vizard, and <hi>Joſebeth</hi> was choſen by Heaven to pull it off.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Manaſſes</hi> was grown in love with her beyond all bounds, and increaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the liberty his Quality gave him of viſiting her every week without controul. That freedom gave him occaſion enough to open his heart intirely to that lovely Woman, or at leaſt to ſound hers, and feel how ſuch a declaration would be received. The ſoft Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:66367:33"/>and great complaiſance of <hi>Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſebeth</hi> gave him ſome hopes; the particular eſteem that ſhe ſhew'd him flattered his deſires, and above all, the coldneſs he perceived ſhe had for her Husband, ſeemed to promiſe him a favourable ſucceſs. But on the other ſide his paſſion did not ſo blind him, but that he feared <hi>Joſebeth</hi> might be of the hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour of ſome cunning Women, who to gain themſelves a reputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Virtue, are pleaſed to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject the offers of ſome old or ill-conditioned Lover, when in the ſame time with greater ſurety they accept another that is more to their mind. Beſides he had a mind if poſſible to ingage <hi>Joſebeth</hi> without changing the part he had ſo long acted of a Saint. This appeared almoſt unpoſſible at firſt, yet having thought well on the buſineſs, he believed he had at laſt hit upon a way ſuitable to his deſign. The
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:66367:33"/>next time that he ſaw <hi>Joſebeth,</hi> he did nothing but entertain her with the hopes he had to ſee their Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on quickly delivered from their miſery by the coming of <hi>Meſſias.</hi> And the next time told her, that he had found out, in reading the Holy Prophets, that the <hi>Meſſias</hi> was to be begot by a Man in years, famous for Learning and Piety, and that had paſſed all his life in Virginity. A little after he read a Letter he had received from the devout <hi>Jews</hi> in <hi>Portugal,</hi> which brought news, that a Propheteſs there had foretold, that the <hi>Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſias</hi> was to be born in <hi>Holland;</hi> which he confirmed by divers Quotations of the old Teſtament, enough to confound a young Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man of two and twenty. In this faſhion did our Rabbin endeavour to prepare her for his holy Intrigue; and at laſt raiſed a Report, that in a ſwooning Fit he had, which was
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:66367:34"/>called, <hi>A Divine Extaſie,</hi> Heaven had revealed to him ſome extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary matter, which he could the eaſier do, by reaſon of that high eſteem all the Synagogue had of him. After, having laid all thoſe Snares for the innocent <hi>Joſebeth,</hi> he went to viſit her, and after hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing inſinuated all his former diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſes about the <hi>Meſſias,</hi> he added to all the reſt with an affected hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility, that an Angel had revealed it to him, that they two were cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen, by Heaven, to give their Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion its long deſired Protector. This wicked ſubtilty was not whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly new in this accurſed Phariſie, for, according to the Tradition of the <hi>Hebrews,</hi> the ſeveral Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crites have uſed the ſame means to accompliſh their wicked deſigns. Such was the way of thoſe Elders, that the young Prophet confound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed at <hi>Babylon;</hi> and ſome of them had the fortune to deceive poor
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:66367:34"/>credulous Women, who injured their Husbands out of pure Zeal. Of which number was <hi>Dina,</hi> a young Woman of <hi>Alexandria,</hi> who being brought to Bed of a Girl, inſtead of the <hi>Deliverer of Iſrael,</hi> which the Rabbin <hi>Simon</hi> had pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed her, went to the Judge to make her Complaint of him, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing more troubled for the diſap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointment of her hopes, than the loſs of her Honour. But how fooliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſoever the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Women might behave themſelves, <hi>Joſebeth</hi> was not to be caught in ſuch a Snare; ſhe had too much wit, not to ſee the Cheat. Though at firſt ſhe received <hi>Manaſſes</hi> propoſition with ſome kind of gayety, the promiſe of bringing a Divine Off-ſpring, having nothing in it but what was very pleaſant to a Woman of her Age and Humour: But ſeriouſly reflecting on his Impudence, ſhe remembred the ſtory ſhe had read
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:66367:35"/>of that prophane Prieſt of the God <hi>Anubis,</hi> who under pretext of Piety, violated the illuſtrious <hi>Paulina;</hi> and ſhe was ſo far from imitating thoſe Heatheniſh Devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, that the Reſpect and Friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip ſhe had before conceived for that Rabbin, were changed into a Horrour and Averſion for him, that never could be diminiſhed. Notwithſtanding, ſhe diſſembled that change ſo cunningly, that he did not perceive it. So that when he preſſed her to diſcover her Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timents of a buſineſs of that im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portance, which, he ſaid, he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municated to her in the ſimplicity of his heart, by the expreſs order of Heaven; ſhe ſeemed ſo ſurpriz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed that ſhe returned no anſwer at all; which made him flatter himſelf with the preſage of a happy ſucceſs; thinking in himſelf, that the moſt one can hope for, from a fine Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, is to ſuffer the firſt declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:66367:35"/>of an unlawful deſire, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out falling into Anger and Rage. In this thought the Rabbin forgot the Divine Revelation, and began to obey the violence of his paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and approach <hi>Joſebeth,</hi> in a very carnal manner, when ſhe made him a ſign, with her Eyes and Hand, that ſhe heard her Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band coming. So much patience in an occaſion when ſhe ought to have none, was not, for all that, an effect of her weakneſs. Her deſign was only to permit <hi>Manaſſes</hi> ſo far as might engage the Credit and Power he had with <hi>Wanbergue,</hi> for the obtaining ſome of her de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires. The Rabbin did not un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand it in that manner, and finding, by the ſigns that <hi>Joſebeth</hi> made him, the preſence of <hi>Wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bergue</hi> did much retard his hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs, he reſolved to find ſome way to ſend him from home for ſome conſiderable time, which
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:66367:36"/>was pretty hard to accompliſh; for the <hi>Hollander</hi> had no buſineſs to draw him from home ſo much as one Night, much leſs to occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him any long Journey, his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors taking ſo much care of his Concerns, that he never ſtirred from home, except it were to go to the <hi>Exchange.</hi> Notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Manaſſes</hi> having taken notice, that nothing was ſo dear to <hi>Wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bergue,</hi> as the intereſt of his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, reſolved to make uſe of that Zeal for the Houſe of the Lord, to get him to abſent him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf from his own; and it was in this manner that he effected his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign. Three Months before, there was come one into <hi>Holland,</hi> a <hi>Frenchman,</hi> named <hi>Deſſous;</hi> a great Mathematician, and one who had particularly applyed himſelf to the ſtudy of Ships, who had found out new ſecrets in order to the building Veſſels in an extraordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:66367:36"/>faſhion. He had preſented a Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morial to the States, and had their leave to employ what Timber and Workmen he thought fit at <hi>Rotter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam,</hi> but all on his own charge.</p>
            <p>The talk of this new Ingineer, and this wonderful Invention, was very fit for <hi>Manaſſes</hi> Project, who having his natural wit ſharpened by Love, uſed a deviſe to ſend a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way the Husband, that never could have entred into any bodies head. He aſſembled together the Rabbins and chief Men of his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, and after having made a great diſcourſe about the coming of the <hi>Meſſias,</hi> he told them, that in the hopes of ſo great a happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs for their Nation, they ought not to neglect any thing that might tend towards the attaining the knowledge of ſuch a felicity. That for his part he had taken no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice in the <hi>Talmud,</hi> that, that King which they expected, was
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:66367:37"/>to have, among other things; Ships of a moſt extraordinary fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhion, that ſo he might the better be enabled to deſtroy by Sea, as well as on Land, any force of the Unbelievers, that would endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to hinder their return into <hi>Judea;</hi> and conſidering that Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſie and the Report that was ſpread abroad of that wonderful Veſſel that was going to be built, he thought the leaſt they could do, was at leaſt to ſend ſome Perſons of Judgment and Integrity to <hi>Rot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terdam,</hi> to inform themſelves ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actly of what was to be learnt, and to give an account of it to the Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagogue.</p>
            <p>The great reputation that <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſſes</hi> had acquired, together with that ſtrong facility the <hi>Jews</hi> have had in all Ages, to be impoſed up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on by the hopes of their <hi>Meſſias,</hi> made all the Aſſembly applaud the Rabbins Propoſition: And as
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:66367:37"/>they were about to conſider of the Perſons they ſhould chuſe for ſuch an Employment, <hi>Manaſſes</hi> cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ningly prevented the queſtion, by ſaying, no Man was ſo fit for that Honour as <hi>Wanbergue.</hi> All the Company approved the choiſe, and <hi>Jonadab,</hi> a Rabby, was appointed to go with him; ſo that they pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared themſelves to begin their Journey the next day, and as they were going away, <hi>Manaſſes</hi> gave them a particular to make their In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiries by, to make the little Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſie appear more conſiderable. In the mean while <hi>Joſebeth</hi> looked upon this Deputation as a ſerious Affair, till the Afternoon, that <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſſes</hi> came to wait on her, and told her, that Providence had or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered this abſence of <hi>Wanbergue,</hi> as being neceſſary for the accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhment of that Myſtery, that they two were to perform. This Diſcourſe, inſtead of working
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:66367:38"/>on <hi>Joſebeth</hi> in his favour, gave her a greater averſion for him than be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, and made her confine her thoughts within her ſelf; <hi>How,</hi> ſaid ſhe, <hi>to abuſe perpetually ſo ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerable and holy a name as that of the</hi> Meſſias, <hi>one while to corrupt a Wife, and then to ſend away a Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band, and always to cover ſome Roguery!</hi> Whiles ſhe was thus en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertaining her ſelf, <hi>Manaſſes,</hi> judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing by her ſilence, of her conſent, and thinking to gain it intirely, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved to attack her where ſhe was weakeſt; for having marked the Fancy ſhe had for extraordinary E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vents, he reſolved now to flatter it; telling her, that ſhe was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved to be the only Perſon in the World, for whom that Honour was kept: And he ſo beat into her Ears the Terms of <hi>rare,</hi> unheard of, <hi>ſingular, particular, priviledges,</hi> and the like, in ſpeaking of the glory ſhe would have in bringing
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:66367:38"/>forth the <hi>Meſſias,</hi> that <hi>Joſebeth,</hi> who in diſdain had held down her Eyes all the while, now began a little to mind what he ſaid; and certainly, if any thing in the World could have moved her, this would. However, the inclination ſhe had for extraordinary accidents, was not ſo ſtrong as her averſion to ſo horrid an impiety; and her thoughts were wholly taken up, how ſhe ſhould eſcape ſo dangerous an Invaſion. But <hi>Manaſſas</hi> put a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother interpretation on her ſilence, and imagined he now had wholly vanquiſhed her: And this imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation enflaming his paſſion, made him forget the part he had ſo long acted of a Saint, and inſtead of that, to give himſelf up to all the tranſports a violent luſtful young Man can uſe; which put <hi>Joſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth</hi> into a greater fright than ever ſhe had been in. <hi>How,</hi> ſays ſhe, <hi>is it in this manner, that you go a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:66367:39"/>to obey the will of Heaven? Is this behaviour ſuitable to the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands the Angels, thoſe pure and holy Spirits, gave you? Manaſſas,</hi> ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that, took up his gravity again, telling her, that he only erred in the manner, and that ſhe could accuſe him of nothing but of exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuting the Divine Command in a way ſomething carnal. <hi>When our Fore-fathers killed the</hi> Amala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kites <hi>they did an action good and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, though perhaps there was mixed in their obedience, ſome ſinful heat and anger.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>In like manner, the fulfilling of the</hi> Divine Revelation, <hi>will not be hindred by thoſe tranſports that your beauty cauſes in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> except, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam, you ſhould fail of that reſpect and docility that you ought to ſhew.</hi> In this manner did this hateful Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrite abuſe his Wit and Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, but to no purpoſe; for <hi>Joſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth,</hi> being enraged with the repe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:66367:39"/>of his inſolence and blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, took a reſolution rather to die, than to let him enjoy his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires. But the <hi>Rabbin,</hi> who ſaw not what paſſed in the Heart of that Gallant Woman, began again his Batteries, thinking that ſhe had on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly a mind to be overcome with force; and in this Conflict the Chamber was quickly ſtrewed with his Cloak, his Gloves, and his Hat, whiles the poor <hi>Joſebeth,</hi> armed only with her modeſty and her anger, undauntedly reſiſted the inſolence of this Monſter.</p>
            <p>In this Conflict, though <hi>Joſebeth</hi> defended her ſelf very well, yet ſhe received ſome blows, which are not to be endured by a Lady; the grief ſhe had, made her at laſt ſeek that ſafety in her Tongue, which her Hands could not give her; but there being no body near her, ſhe ran for ſuccour to a new diſſimulation, the moſt uſual, and
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:66367:40"/>the beſt Arms that Women can imploy; and ſpeaking very ſoftly, <hi>What pleaſure can you have in open day, were it not better ſtay till night; that might a little hide my bluſhes, and take too from my ſight, that Reverent Aſpect of yours, which now gives me rather Fear than Love, and makes me look on you rather as my Father, than my Gallant? Manaſſas</hi> fancied, 'twas only a little ſcruple of Modeſty that retained her, which with the help of the Night he ſhould eaſily overcome. <hi>I will obey you,</hi> ſaid he, <hi>and defer my joy till night, and at Eleven a Clock I will not fail to come: And you, my Dear,</hi> ſaid he, with the voice of a ſoft and gentle Conquerour, <hi>prepare your ſelf to receive the greateſt Honour that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver Woman had.</hi> And ſaying ſo, he went and took a little Key that o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened the door into the Garden which lay before <hi>Joſebeths</hi> Apart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:66367:40"/>for he meant to come into her Chamber that way, as being the moſt eaſie and commodious. She let him take it, and to be rid of him the ſooner, promiſed to leave her Chamber door open, and that another little Gate that was in the midſt of a great Baluſtrade of Iron, that ſeparated a little Court from the Garden, ſhould on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be put too. With theſe hopes the <hi>Rabbin</hi> went away, his eyes ſparkling with fire, which <hi>Joſebeth</hi> was ſorry to have kindled, eſteem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it the greateſt misfortune of her life.</p>
            <p>Twice ſhe had hid her Reſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, with a Prudence not to be expected from one of her Age; but when he was gone, the affront ſhe had received made her burſt out into tears, and drown her Heart with ſighs, which ſhe did not interrupt, unleſs it were to curſe the Synagogue, and all the
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:66367:41"/>Race of the <hi>Jews. What,</hi> ſaid ſhe, <hi>theſe be the Men whom we eſteem like Prophets, and adore like the Vice-Roys of Heaven here on Earth, who Preach ſo often, that we muſt not ſo much as look upon another mans Wife with deſire! What Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digies are theſe,</hi> ſaid ſhe, and lift<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up her eyes to Heaven, <hi>good God, is it poſſible that that can be thy Law, which is publiſhed by the mouth of ſuch men, who break it with ſo much inſolence.</hi> The extremity of <hi>Joſebeth</hi>'s grief and rage, hindred her from ſeeing, that a Religion may be good, though the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of it be never ſo bad. But that is a popular way of arguing, and though generally it does a great deal of miſchief, yet now it did ſome good, by preparing her mind for ſomething extraordinary. <hi>Solomoune,</hi> that came into her Chamber without asking leave, found her in this ſad condition, and
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:66367:41"/>did what ſhe could to comfort her, by making new Aſſurances of her Fidelity and readineſs to do what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever ſhe commanded her: And af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſome talk, they reſolved to have Supper made ready later than or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary, that the Servants ſhould ſit up longer, that ſo <hi>Manaſſas</hi> being tired with watching about the houſe, might retire of his own ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord. This was executed accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly, and it was now mid-night, when contrary to the cuſtom of that Country, there appeared light in moſt of the Windows of the Houſe.</p>
            <p>The truth is, the <hi>Rabbin</hi> was a little tired with waiting, for he had been there ſince ten a Clock, and thought the time very long; but for all that he never thought of going away, though it began to rain moſt cruelly, and there was not any ſhelter to ſave his new Beaver, his Point <hi>de Venice</hi> Band, and his Velvet Coat, which he had
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:66367:42"/>tricked up himſelf withall, to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear with better Meen before his Miſtreſs. 'Twas well for her that it was moſt horrible dark, that ſo neither the Neighbours, or any of her own Servants, might ſee a Man walking in her Garden at that time of Night, and in her Husbands ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence: For her part, that knew he was there, ſhe could diſcern him well enough, and ſaw, that though he looked like a drown'd Rat, yet he did not look as if he would go away. 'Twas ſo late, that ſhe or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered her People to go to Bed, thinking her ſelf ſufficiently ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, by having the door of the Baluſtrade, and that of her Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, well locked. <hi>Manaſſas,</hi> who, contrary to his expectation, found the door firſt of the Baluſtrade ſhut, flattered himſelf with the belief, that 'twas ſome miſtake of the Servants; and therefore being no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing diſheartened, and ſeeing no
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:66367:42"/>more light in the Windows, he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved to get over the Baluſtrade of Iron as well as he could, though it was very high from the ground; yet he did ſo well, getting in his feet by the ſide of the Iron-bar that faſtned the Baluſtrade to the cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of the Wall, that at laſt he clamber'd up to the top of the Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſtrade. <hi>Joſebeth,</hi> that ſaw him all the while out of her Window, pulled <hi>Solomoune,</hi> and laughing, ſaid, <hi>See there the Patriarch of our Synagogue most delicately perch'd; is it not a pretty way of obeying Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Revelations?</hi> Poor <hi>Solomoune</hi> looked very ſeriouſly, and told her Miſtreſs, <hi>ſhe could not chuſe but pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty him: I adviſe you,</hi> ſaid <hi>Joſebeth,</hi> giving her a good bang, <hi>to fall a crying: Why,</hi> ſaid the Nurſe, <hi>'tis natural to have compaſſion on any thing that loves us, eſpecially a man of that conſideration. 'Tis on that accompt,</hi> ſaid <hi>Joſebeth, that he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:66367:43"/>no pity; if a man of his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration, had done nothing but ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded the Law a Sundays, and of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer'd Incenſe on the New Moons, I ſhould have continued my Friendſhip for him for ever; but ſeeing he forgets his Profeſſion, and his Age, to run into the extravagancies of Love and Youth, that he laughs at his Religion, nay abuſes it, the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to deſtroy my Honour, there is nothing in the World that I deſpiſe ſo much as this Fallen Angel.</hi> Whiles they were talking, the <hi>Rab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bin</hi> was come down into the little Court before her Chamber, very eaſily, becauſe the ground on that ſide was raiſed higher than the Garden, and filled up almoſt half the Baluſtrade; he was no ſooner down, but he ran to the door that opened out of the Chamber, and finding it ſhut contrary to his ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectations, he was almoſt mad, and began to think, that they had
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:66367:43"/>played him a trick: However, not to be wanting in any thing, he ſcratched a good while at the door, and though it continued raining extremely, yet he ſtayed a little longer, coughed, and threw little ſtones againſt the Window, till at laſt he had wakened <hi>Joſebeth</hi>'s Spaniels, that made ſuch a bark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that <hi>Manaſſas,</hi> for fear he might be caught, began to climb up the Baluſtrade; and though it were very high from the ground to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the Garden, yet he thought he might ſlide down without any great trouble; as indeed he might eaſily have done, if in paſſing the Baluſtrade, his Velvet Coat had not unluckily hung in the Spikes of Iron that were ſet all along on the top of the Baluſtrade; he did not perceive it, till the weight of his body having made the Spikes enter fully into his Coat, he found himſelf ſtaid by it, dangling in the
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:66367:44"/>air: and after having ſtruggled all he could, the Coat being new and ſtrong, he was fain to unbutton himſelf, and leave the Coat hang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on the Iron: He durſt not ſtay any longer, for a huge noiſe of laughter at the Window, and the noiſe the Spaniels made with bark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, hearing him fall into the Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, made the poor man run as faſt as he could to the Garden door, which he ſhut very ſoftly af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter him. <hi>Joſebeth</hi> was ready to die with laughing, and ſhe thought it was ſome piece of Juſtice, that the ſame Man who had given her ſo much trouble the ſame day, ſhould afford her ſo much diverſion at night: But for all her mirth, ſhe forgot not to ſend <hi>Solomoune</hi> for the Velvet Coat, which being wet through, they imagined its Maſter was in a fine pickle: <hi>Alas,</hi> ſaid <hi>Solomoune,</hi> conſidering his age, and the cold he muſt needs take, <hi>it
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:66367:44"/>will certainly coſt him his life; and you will be, Madam, doubly the cauſe of his death. Let him live or die,</hi> ſays <hi>Joſebeth, let him love or hate me, I care not, I am only glad to ſee my ſelf freed from his Inſolence it preſent, and for the time to come from his importunities; for after this uſage, I ſuppoſe I ſhall no more be troubled with them. Manaſſas,</hi> by that time he came home, was of the ſame mind, and reſolved in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of making her any more of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers of Love, to ſhew her all the effects of his hate that he could: he fell into ſo deep a melancholly, that when the Deputies were come back from <hi>Rotterdam,</hi> eight days after their ſetting out from <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterdam,</hi> and that they waited up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him to give him an accompt of their Journey, which afforded no great matter of hope, he heard their Relation with an unconcern, that very much ſurprized them.
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:66367:45"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="85" facs="tcp:66367:45"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="86" facs="tcp:66367:46"/>All this was paſſed but a Month before the Adventure of <hi>Villeneufe,</hi> and without doubt it had been an excellent occaſion for our <hi>Rabbin</hi> to have revenged himſelf on <hi>Joſebeth</hi> in the Profanation of the Syna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gogue, if he had been as lucky to have diſcovered, as the Lovers were indiſcreet in making ſuch an appointment for their diverſion, in a place where he had ſo many Spies, and ſo much power. When <hi>Solomoune</hi> had told <hi>Villeneufe</hi> this ſtory, he was frighted at the dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger they had paſſed, and he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded, that both his Miſtreſs and he muſt uſe more diſcretion for the time to come. He charged the Nurſe to give her that advice, till he could come himſelf to inculcate it; and to ſhew her a good exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, he reſolved not to ſtir out of the houſe where he was, till it was dark. Afterwards he put off his Womans Cloaths to put on his
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:66367:46"/>own; but he was as long in un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſing, as the Ladies uſe to be a dreſſing; for every part of <hi>Joſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth</hi>'s Cloaths that he pulled off, gave him occaſion to fall into ſome Contemplation or other, that kept him a good while: And when he came to her Smock, as he was pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling it over his head, there came in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to it the moſt ridiculous fancy that ever was, which he immediately executed; for, laying the Smock at length on the Table before him, he took that part of it before, that was to be next her Heart, and wrote in it theſe Verſes, making the Smock ſpeak.</p>
            <q>
               <l>I, Lovers, that have felt each pant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing heart</l>
               <l>Beat in its breaſt, without the dreſs of Art,</l>
               <l>Can ſafely ſay, that Nature did de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign,</l>
               <l>Your loving hearts in equal Bonds ſhould joyn.</l>
            </q>
            <pb n="88" facs="tcp:66367:47"/>
            <p>The things that Love make peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple do, appear ridiculous to thoſe who have not their hearts warm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with that paſſion, but yet have much weight and myſtery with the amorous themſelves: this writing on the Smock was one of Loves fooleries, and yet <hi>Villeneufe</hi> was very much pleaſed with himſelf, for having found out ſuch an extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vagant way of ſhewing his affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and hoped that it would pleaſe his Miſtreſs, if it were only for the newneſs of the invention. He gave it <hi>Solomoune,</hi> and bid her car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry it to her Miſtreſs, and prayed her to inſinuate ſlily, that this was a piece of Gallantry that had never been practiſed before; for though it was no great matter in it ſelf, yet he hoped ſhe might be taken with its ſingularity. And being now alone, he reſolved to ſee what 'twas that he had ſtole in the Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagogue, which he had taken out
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:66367:47"/>of the Pocket of his Miſtreſſes Coat, before he ſent it away. He unfolded the little Pacquet, and found rowled up in two or three Papers, a little Picture of a Lady in Mourning, that ſeemed to be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout thirty years old, that had ſo fine an air, that without <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 chunk">
                  <desc>…</desc>
               </gap>g the Idea of <hi>Joſebeth</hi> in ones head, one could not have eſcaped being very much taken with it. <hi>I ſhall not be long in the doubt who ſhe is,</hi> ſaid <hi>Ville neufe, for certainly theſe Papers will instruct me fully.</hi> The firſt that he opened was a Letter, with this Inſcription, <hi>For</hi> Abigal <hi>that is never at home:</hi> it appeared to be a Mans Hand; and thus it was.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <p>
                     <hi>'TIs hard, Madam, to come four days together, at ſeveral hours, and not find you once! to run after you in all the places where one gueſſes you might be, and be told at
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:66367:48"/>every houſe, that you are but juſt gone thence! how is it poſſible for me, after this, to be ſo contented with my Priſon, as you would have me think I have reaſon to be? I would give half the blood in my Veins, that you were in this of</hi> Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſebeths <hi>humour, that is always at home. The truth is, your Picture would a little conſole me for the troubles thoſe Eclipſes give me, would to God it could conſole me too, for a loſs I have by a Factor at</hi> Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noa, <hi>of almoſt ten thouſand pound, and a Ship of mine the Pyrates of</hi> Algier <hi>have taken. But if you are really pleaſed with the offers I make you of my ſervice, and all the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns I have to gain you, you muſt, if you pleaſe, govern your ſelf in quite another manner.</hi>
                  </p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>When he had done, he could not forbear laughing: <hi>This is right a</hi> Dutch <hi>Gallantry,</hi> ſays he, <hi>and the
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:66367:48"/>true ſtile of</hi> Cupid <hi>writing out of a Ware-houſe: what tenderneſs of Love, and what fine Complements? I ſhall hate</hi> Abigal, <hi>if ſhe be capable to uſe ſuch a Brute kindly; but I ſhall ſee that by her Anſwer.</hi> He had it ready in the next Paper that he opened, and 'twas this.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <p>
                     <hi>IF you could do any thing elſe but grumble, you would be ſo far from chiding, that you would be pleaſed to bid me joy, in being freed from the bondage, which, for two years, the Ceremony to be obſerved by a Widdow has kept me in: Not that I deſign to uſe my liberty in the way that you would have me; no, I pretend to ſpend it in Duty and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, as you may ſee by the place where I writ this Letter, which is in one of the Tents of our Syna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gogue, where I am like to paſs a night very ill, if the pleaſure of enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining my ſelf with the thought
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:66367:49"/>and hopes of our Love, does not help to divert me: So that I ſhall divide my ſelf betwixt you and the</hi> Rab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bins; <hi>they ſhall have the Ceremony, and you the Subſtance. The cuſtom I have of being kind to you, draws theſe Expreſſions from me before I think on't, for you do no ways de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve them, and leſs do you deſerve the Picture you ask; however I ſend it you, on condition, that the Mourn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing you ſee me dreſſed in, make you remember, that I am free to beſtow my heart on him that ſhall make me love him moſt: I do not mean to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrain my Inclinations.</hi>
                  </p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>This Letter, that was not finiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, ſufficiently ſhewed of what Character <hi>Abigal</hi> was; which <hi>Villeneufe</hi> eaſily found out, and had ſuch a contempt for her, that throwing down her Letter, <hi>What a pitiful ſort of Woman is this, the meanneſs of her Soul deſtroys the
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:66367:49"/>Beauty of her Face. Oh</hi> Joſebeth, <hi>my lovely</hi> Joſebeth, <hi>is another ſort of Creature! how graceful is ſhe when ſhe would be ſevere, and how obliging is ſhe in that ſeverity it ſelf?</hi> That thought ſet him a-work for ſome time. At laſt he continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; <hi>As for</hi> Abigal, <hi>ſhe muſt needs be an ill Woman, and this Letter is but an ill Picture of her mind.</hi> There was but one Paper more to read; and when <hi>Villeneufe</hi> had opened it, he ſaw 'twas a Cypher to write ſecretly, with a Key of Signs to ſpeak by in Publick. The writing was not the ſame hand with the other Letters, and it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared to be newly done, and brought thither, in all likelihood, to be either ſtudied, or copied. After having examined theſe Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers, he was a little ſurprized, though bred up in the Army, and the Court, two Places that do not uſually give great impreſſions of
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:66367:50"/>Piety, to have found people ſo im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed in a place and time ſo ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnly devoted to the Divine Worſhip. <hi>If the</hi> Jewiſh <hi>Women do perform the other parts of their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion,</hi> ſaid he, <hi>like this Feaſt of Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bernacles, I perceive</hi> Moſes<hi>'s Law will be neatly kept.</hi> As he was in theſe thoughts, <hi>Solomoune</hi> came in, and he had but juſt time to rowl up the Papers, and put them in his Pocket: <hi>I come,</hi> ſaid ſhe, <hi>from wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king my Miſtreſs, and never did ſhe laugh ſo much in her life, as ſhe has done on reading your Verſes upon her Smock; and yet at laſt ſhe began to be a little melancholly, looking on thoſe words,</hi> Nature did deſign your loving hearts in equal Bonds ſhould joyn. <hi>I wiſh to God,</hi> ſaid ſhe, ſighing, <hi>that it be as true as that I think I deſire we were made one for another, and that the Event may make good my thoughts, and my de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires: afterwards ſhe fell into her
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:66367:50"/>pleaſant humour again, as you will ſee by this Note which ſhe has ſent you. Villeneufe</hi> took it trembling, and found theſe words:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>I thought that I had been, when I pleaſed, the moſt extravagant Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture in the World, but now your Verſes have robbed me of that glory. The ſtuff, as well as the faſhion, are equally bizarre, and the part where you have writ them, make up all: So on the whole matter, my Smock is now fit for a Romance, and from henceforwards it ſhall be my Holy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day Smock; with precaution how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, which I think as neceſſary as you can do: Therefore do you and</hi> Solomoune <hi>take your meaſure toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and I ſhall agree to whatever you reſolve on.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That reſolution was, that he ſhould not ſee <hi>Joſebeth</hi> in eight days, but that he ſhould ſend his Man with a Letter to <hi>Solomounes</hi> little Houſe every night.</p>
            <pb n="96" facs="tcp:66367:51"/>
            <p>As <hi>Solomoune</hi> was about to get him ſome Supper, he asked in a careleſs manner, as if it were by chance, and for want of other diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, if ſhe knew one called <hi>Abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gal,</hi> and whether it were the Name of a Man or a Woman: <hi>You need ask no body but</hi> Joſebeth, ſaid the Nurſe, not ſtirring from what ſhe was about, <hi>and it may help to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance your buſineſs bravely. But who told you any thing of</hi> Abigal? <hi>Two or three people,</hi> ſaid he, <hi>that talked under the Window before you came in, named that Name ſo of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, that it ſtuck in my memory, and I thought to ask you who 'twas. Come hither,</hi> ſays <hi>Solomoune,</hi> ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king him by the arm, <hi>do you ſee o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver thoſe Gardens, that fine Houſe, with the great Windows, that is</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bigals <hi>Houſe: But if you will ſwear to ſay nothing to my Miſtreſs, I will tell you more? She was born at</hi> Bruſſels, <hi>where her Father, who was
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:66367:51"/>a</hi> Spaniard, <hi>but for his Religion was a ſecret</hi> Jew, <hi>had a conſiderable Employment in the Court of the Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinal</hi> Infanta, <hi>Governour of</hi> Flan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders. <hi>The Agent of</hi> Portugal <hi>that reſided at</hi> Amſterdam, <hi>having ſeen her in a Journey he had occaſion to make to</hi> Bruſſels, <hi>deſired her for his Wife, and was preferred to a great many others, becauſe he (as you know ſince the Expulſion of the</hi> Moors <hi>and</hi> Jews <hi>out of</hi> Spain, <hi>there remain a great many ſecret</hi> Jews) <hi>was of the ſame Religion with her Father</hi> Dom Gomez.</p>
            <p>In a little while he left her a rich Widow; and as ſoon as in decency ſhe could, ſhe took another Husband, of the ſame Nation and Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on with her firſt, his name was <hi>Caladujar,</hi> whom ſhe has already buried, and by that means is again at her diſpoſe, and ſurely ſhe is one of the handſomeſt Women in <hi>Holland.</hi> She pretends to know
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:66367:52"/>the World better than any of our Ladies here, becauſe ſhe lived with her Father in the Court of <hi>Bruſſels;</hi> ſo that all things are carried with a great Air in her Houſe, and ſhe allows her ſelf a greater liberty than our Women uſually take: they ſay ſhe loves nothing ſo much as her pleaſure; perhaps 'tis but a ſcandal, for ſhe goes devoutly to the Synagogue; but however ſhe has that Reputation. <q>And how are the Rabbins pleas'd with this,</q> 
               <hi>ſaid</hi> Villeneufe. <hi>Among the</hi> Jews, ſaid Solomoune, <hi>the Widows are allowed a much greater liberty than married Women, or Maids, for rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons that I do not remember, and under that pretence</hi> Abigal <hi>takes a little too much: ſhe has been ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral times reproved for it, and</hi> Manaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſas, <hi>as well as the other Rabbins, have ſometimes ſhew'd their diſlike of her way of living, but none has ſpoke ſo home as</hi> Joſaphat, <hi>who is the moſt
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:66367:52"/>learned and vertuous of them all. He preached at the great Feaſt of Expiation, that is the</hi> 10th <hi>day of</hi> September; <hi>and was ſo particular in condemning the liberty of Widows, that it was plain enough he meant</hi> Abigal. <hi>However his Exhortati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, did no good, through the malice of the other Rabbins, who taking an occaſion to ſcandalize him, becauſe he has no Beard, ſay, he cryes out a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Women, only becauſe the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfection of his Nature gives him an averſion for them. Beſides,</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bigal <hi>has ſuch a way to flatter and ingratiate her ſelf with all the World, that it takes very little no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of what ſhe does.</hi> 
               <q>But after all, <hi>ſays Villeneufe,</hi> what has <hi>Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſebeth</hi> to do with <hi>Abigal?</hi> Oh, <hi>ſays the Nurſe,</hi> that is the Secret; and yet, <hi>ſaid ſhe,</hi> (that long'd to tell all ſhe knew) I can't forbear giving you this Mark of my truſt, ſo much I eſteem you. You muſt
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:66367:53"/>know then, that <hi>Wanbergue</hi> fell deſperately in Love with <hi>Abigal</hi> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter her firſt Husband dyed. They are both much about the ſame age, and I cannot tell by what kind of ſimpathy, ſhe loved him at the ſame time, ſo that he uſed all his endeavours with his Father, to have his conſent to Marry her. But the good old Man, that did not like her free way of living, oppoſed it firmly, and did the more eagerly embrace the firſt Propoſition that <hi>Joſebeths</hi> Father made him about the ſame time. The happineſs of poſſeſſing ſo fine a Woman as <hi>Joſebeth,</hi> has not ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken away the firſt love he had for <hi>Abigal;</hi> he has ſtill continued to viſit her, and, betwixt you and I, I believe he ſtill adores her. You may eaſily imagine what an inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry this is to <hi>Joſebeth,</hi> and how hainouſly ſhe takes it. 'Tis not that <hi>Joſebeth</hi> values the love of
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:66367:53"/>her Husband, but it cannot but out her to the heart to ſee another ſo unjuſtly preferr'd before her; for though <hi>Abigal</hi> be very hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome, yet I aſſure you ſhe cannot be compared to <hi>Joſebeth,</hi> either in Youth, Beauty, or Wit.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Villeneufe</hi> was of <hi>Solomoun</hi>'s opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, and thought that <hi>Wanbergue</hi> did his Miſtreſs a great injury, but however he was not much troubled at it, becauſe it advanced his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns: And beginning to eſteem the Nurſe, as a Woman of good ſenſe and breeding, he amuſed himſelf a little in diſcourſing with her. <q>I know very well, <hi>ſaid he,</hi> that Ladies eſteem ſo much the Reputation of Beauty, and hold it ſo dear, that though they have ever ſome averſion for a Man, yet it can never go ſo far, as to make them deſire, he ſhould carry his ſighs and ſervices any where elſe. As much diſdain as you pleaſe,
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:66367:54"/>but a fair Lady will ſtill look on the going away of a Lover, whom ſhe did not value, as the loſs of a Subject, and a diminution of her Empire, and never will ſhe forgive that Fugitive, that, though ill uſed, durſt ingage himſelf in the ſervice of another Miſtreſs. But dear Miſtreſs <hi>Solomoune, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued Villeneufe, having a mind to paſs away the time,</hi> let us know a little of your Concerns, and tell me a little what Company you have kept, to get ſo much wit as you ſhew in all your diſcourſe.</q>
               <q>You laugh at me, <hi>ſaid ſhe,</hi> but I have read ſomething in my time, and there have been Men in the World, that could think it worth their while to entertain me.</q>
               <q>By what I yet ſee, <hi>ſaid Villeneufe,</hi> I judge you have made no incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable Conqueſts; but may one not know ſome one of the Slaves you have made.</q>
               <q>Yes, <hi>ſaid ſhe,
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:66367:54"/>growing young again with the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance of paſt pleaſure,</hi> I have been loved; and it would be no Romance, if I ſhould tell you there was a time when a Marſhal of <hi>France</hi> had no other inclination but for me. I was but eighteen years old, when he ſaid I had too much wit for a <hi>Lorrainer,</hi> and he did our Family many a good turn for my ſake. As he came back from an Ambaſſie in <hi>Switzerland,</hi> he came forty miles out of his way to ſee me; and he proteſted, that if ever he publiſhed the Sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of his Life, I ſhould not be for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten.</q>
               <q>Oh, <hi>ſaid Villeneufe,</hi> this muſt be the Marſhal of <hi>Ba</hi>—</q>
               <q>You are in the right, <hi>ſaid Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moune,</hi> and I was acquainted with him, by reaſon my Father held a Farm belonging to the Lordſhip of <hi>Harovel,</hi> which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long'd to the Marſhal. One need not ask if a Lover of that Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:66367:55"/>had reaſon to complain of your cruelty? Alas, <hi>ſaid the poor Nurſe,</hi> 'twas ſo worthy a Man, that 'twas impoſſible—But you laugh at me, and I am a Fool to talk to you ſo, and hinder you from writing to <hi>Joſebeth,</hi> before you go home.</q> He writ a Letter full of reſpect and paſſion, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſought her by eagerneſs of Love, that ſhe would ſhorten the term of eight days, which he himſelf had agreed to, and let him ſee her at the end of three.</p>
            <p>Before <hi>Solomoune</hi> went away, he asked her, if by chance ſhe had not ſomething or other about her of the hand-writing of <hi>Wanbergue; for,</hi> ſays he, <hi>I have a fancy to know his hand.</hi> She look'd in her Pocket, and found a Note of ſome things that he ordered her to buy him two or three days before: <hi>Oh, this is enough,</hi> ſays <hi>Villeneufe;</hi> and as ſoon as ſhe was gone, he took
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:66367:55"/>the Letters out of his Pocket that he had ſtole in the Synagogue, and comparing one of them with this Note the Nurſe had juſt given him, he found they were both the ſame hand. At firſt he did not know, whether he ought to be an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry or glad; for as on one ſide he conſidered, that it muſt needs do him ſervice to convince <hi>Joſebeth</hi> of the Infidelity of her Husband; ſo on the other ſide, the love and eſteem he had for her, made him ſee with indignation, the brutality of a Man that could neglect a Woman of her Merit, for another that was ſo much her inferiour in all reſpects. He was thinking with himſelf, whether he ſhould make his Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſs acquainted with this ſtory; <hi>For,</hi> ſaid he, <hi>one muſt treat Women of wit, and that value their Repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, in another manner than one uſes thoſe that have not ſo much niceneſs and honour; for thoſe are
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:66367:56"/>alarm'd with hearing a ſtory of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother woman, and the fear of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing talked of themſelves, makes them preach againſt the vanity of the world, and renounce to a friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip for ſix Months together, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ever caring what becomes of their Friend all that while: What know I, but that when</hi> Joſebeth <hi>hears, that an intrigue of another woman has been brought to light in ſo extraordinary a manner, ſhe may take a fancy, and be reſerved her ſelf, for fear that her own Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern may ſome way or other be found out too. Villeneufe</hi> had ſuch thoughts, becauſe he did well com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend of what nature were <hi>Joſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beths</hi> intentions for him; and therefore reſolved to tell her no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of the diſcovery he had made of her Husbands love with <hi>Abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gal:</hi> Immediately <hi>Solomoune</hi> came in; <hi>I ſhall tell you ſtrange news,</hi> ſaid ſhe, <hi>who do you think I have left
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:66367:56"/>with my Miſtreſs? Why</hi> Manaſſas, <hi>ſaid</hi> Villeneuſe. <hi>No, 'tis not he, but I ſhould rather have expected to have found him there, than this o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Perſon, for 'tis</hi> Abigal, <hi>who has not been with my Miſtreſs this three years till now, and it muſt be ſomething extraordinary that brings her now.</hi> The Nurſe was in the right, for <hi>Abigal</hi> was extreamly troubled at the loſs of her Papers, and yet could not tell who to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe; and though ſhe did not uſe to be much concerned at any thing, yet now her indifference for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſook her, and ſhe could not with patience think in what Hands, thoſe Letters and her Picture might fall. However, as 'tis natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral, when one is ſurprized, to think it comes from them whom we have injured, <hi>Abigal</hi> who knew <hi>Joſebeth</hi> had been that night in the Synagogue, did ſtrongly ſuſpect 'twas ſhe that had ſtole her Papers.
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:66367:57"/>Being big with this thought, ſhe writ early in the morning to <hi>Wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bergue,</hi> that he ſhould come and ſpeak with her. He fell into a vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent paſſion, when ſhe told him the buſineſs; and when ſhe nam'd <hi>Joſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth, I had rather loſe one of my Ships,</hi> ſaid he, <hi>that are coming home, than that Imperious Woman ſhould have ſuch an advantage over me:</hi> and at laſt he uſed <hi>Abigal</hi> as rudely, as if ſhe had been already his Wife, and that had grievouſly offended him: But ſhe that knew how to order that haſty humour, eaſily brought him to himſelf, and made him perceive, that that misfortune was occaſion<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by her violent affection, and the extraordinary Concern ſhe had to ſhew it, even when ſhe ought to have imployed her thoughts in Devotion: And if any body had reaſon to be troubled, 'twas ſhe, who had loſt both her Letter, and her Picture, by the too eager deſire
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:66367:57"/>ſhe had to ſend them to him. At laſt they both concluded that <hi>Abigal</hi> ſhould pay <hi>Joſebeth</hi> a Viſit, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour in her Converſation to find out what ſhe could of the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venture.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Joſebeth</hi> was about to ſay ſhe was not within, when ſhe ſaw <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bigal</hi> come to viſit her; but the pride ſhe took to be always at home, made her ſuffer that Viſit, though much againſt her humour. She received her with a great cold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, which did not wear off, though <hi>Abigal</hi> made her all the Careſſes and Flatteries in the World. She commended <hi>Joſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth</hi>'s Beauty above all the Ladies in Town; and afterwards fell to talk of the Feaſt of the Taberna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles, and of the diſorder that hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen'd that night <hi>Joſebeth</hi> was at the Synagogue: <q>One cannot, <hi>ſaid Abigal,</hi> diſcover all the Rogueries that are practiſed there, and the
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:66367:58"/>poor Creature that was taken, is not the only prophane Wretch, that abuſed the Devotion of ſuch a holy place, and ſuch a Solemn Feaſt, to have an opportunity of taking that which does not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long to them.</q> 
               <hi>Joſebeth,</hi> that took her words in another meaning than what <hi>Abigal</hi> intended, was mortal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly frighted, and in her heart believ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſhe was found out. However, having naturally a ſteddineſs of mind that was ſeen even in her countenance, ſhe was no way diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordered; but on the contrary, ſhe did not only deteſt the impiety of thoſe people that come into holy places with ill deſigns, but ſpake with great zeal againſt thoſe that imploy their thoughts in places of Devotion, to any thing but that Service which they come there to Celebrate. This diſcourſe frighted <hi>Abigal,</hi> as much as hers had a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larm'd <hi>Joſebeth;</hi> and it had been a
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:66367:58"/>pleaſant thing to ſee thoſe two Women fright one another, with the diſcourſe they held, with no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther deſign, but to keep themſelves from being thought guilty. Of the two, <hi>Abigal</hi> was the moſt frighted, and <hi>Joſebeths</hi> Anſwer made her colour riſe, ſo that ſhe could not hide it: and having ſtayed about half an hour longer with a great conſtraint, at laſt went away without having been able to learn any thing of <hi>Joſebeth,</hi> who was a little come to her ſelf, after the firſt fright that Converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion had given her; but yet had a great impatience to confer with <hi>Villeneufe</hi> upon that Subject: So that having read the Note he ſent her, that <hi>Solomoune</hi> had took an occaſion to give her, while <hi>Abigal</hi> was there, ſhe wrote him another, to come to <hi>Solomoune</hi>'s at the end of three days, as he deſired, but that he ſhould be ſure not to come
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:66367:59"/>in till it was dark night, nor go out till it was very dark. <hi>Villeneufe</hi> obeyed thoſe Orders exactly, and left not the Nurſe till paſt ten a Clock, having her promiſe that ſhe would be there again next night at the ſame hour, that he might ſend her a Letter for his Miſtreſs. Next night <hi>Dumareſt,</hi> that had took good notice of the Houſe, found it, and her there, and gave her a Letter from his Maſter. As ſoon as <hi>Joſebeth</hi> ſaw it, and ſaw a drop of blood about it, which made her Heart beat, ſhe opened it, and read theſe Verſes writ in blood.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Thou that haſt left the Streams of Life to gain</l>
               <l>A Kiſs from <hi>Cloris</hi> hand, tell her the pain,</l>
               <l>The cruel anguiſh, and the killing ſmart,</l>
               <l>That thou didſt feel in paſſing through my Heart.</l>
            </q>
            <pb n="113" facs="tcp:66367:59"/>
            <p>The Verſes were very indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent ones; but coming from a Man in Love, and being writ in Blood too, made them appear quite other things. But the ſenſe of them was not plain to <hi>Joſebeth,</hi> which made her ſend <hi>Solomoune</hi> to ſee in what condition <hi>Villeneufe</hi> might be: <hi>Dumareſt</hi> told her, that his Maſter having found himſelf extreamly heated all night, had been let blood, but that now he was very well, and would not fail of waiting on <hi>Joſebeth</hi> at the time agreed. <q>This is a pretty cheap way of ſhewing ones paſſion, <hi>ſaid Joſebeth,</hi> laughing at the bloody Letters, and a great conveniency of taking care of health, and giving marks of Love at the ſame time:</q>
               <q>Oh, <hi>ſays Solomoune,</hi> you are too hard to be pleaſed; would you have the poor man give him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf a wound indeed, that he might ſend you ſome of his blood
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:66367:60"/>in a Complement; for to do ſo, he muſt be in a more deſpairing condition, than your goodneſs is like to reduce him to.</q>
               <q>Very well, <hi>ſaid Joſebeth,</hi> thou ſeeſt I have a mind to be merry; and taking a Pen in her hand, ſent him this Anſwer.</q>
            </p>
            <q>
               <l>Cheriſh the Stream that runs with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in thy Veins,</l>
               <l>And by thy own increaſe, not <hi>Cloris</hi> pains:</l>
               <l>For know that ſhe will ever bear her part,</l>
               <l>In all the ſufferings of a loyal heart.</l>
            </q>
            <p>Theſe verſes were not made by <hi>Sappho,</hi> but however might paſs, being of a Womans hand, that did not at all pretend to Poetry, nor Rime, except when ſhe had a mind to fool; But <hi>Villeneufe</hi> was charm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with them, and ſaid they were
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:66367:60"/>the beſt that ever he ſaw. In the mean time he had a certain Curi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oſity to ſee <hi>Abigal,</hi> that he might have the pleaſure to laugh at their folly, who compared her to <hi>Joſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth.</hi> With that deſign he went next day to the Synagogue, believ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that <hi>Joſebeth</hi> would not come thither that day; and he only minded who went out and in at the fifth Tent, in which he had found the Picture and the Papers. A great many Women had paſſed by him that were not very likely to be what he ſought; when at laſt he ſaw one, that took up his looks more than all the reſt. She was dreſſed very plain, becauſe the Law ſorbids any finery at that Feaſt; but her ſhape was of it ſelf ſo fine, and there appeared ſuch a Majeſtick Air in her gate, and in the lower part of her Face, that a Vail of Gare that came to her Mouth, diſcovered, that made <hi>Vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leneufe</hi>
               <pb n="116" facs="tcp:66367:61"/>conclude it muſt be <hi>Abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gal.</hi> Having an impatience to know, he ſtopp'd a Woman that followed her, with ſomething un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der her Arm; juſt as he ſaw the firſt go into the fifth Tent, as he thought ſhe would. If all the reſt be anſwerable to as much of her as I have ſeen, ſhe muſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed be very beautiful: he had a mind to ſee how ſhe look'd with her long Mantle on, as ſhe ſtood in her row among the other Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men: ſhe was taller by almoſt the Head, and held her Bough with a certain grace, peculiar to her ſelf. As he beheld her in that poſture, he could not hinder himſelf from making Reflexions one would not have expected from him. <q>How true it is, <hi>ſaid he,</hi> that Hypocri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie it ſelf is a homage that Vice renders to Virtue, and a confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of its excellence: For the wicked, by conſtraining them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:66367:61"/>to an appearance of good, do thereby own that there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing ſo deſirable, as a real Repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of probity: And me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinks <hi>Abigal</hi> her ſelf, who I know in my Conſcience is an ill Woman; yet in that out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Figure of Devotion ſhe ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears ſo lovely, that that falſe appearance makes me almoſt for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get what I know her to be; and I warrant you, ſhe her ſelf is well pleaſed with this ſhew of Religion, that by it ſhe may keep ſome pretence to it. But thoſe thoughts all ended in <hi>Joſebeth,</hi> as 'tis natural for thoſe that have a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny particular Fancy that governs in their Head, to reduce all things to it.</q>
               <q>I confeſs, <hi>ſaid he,</hi> that <hi>Joſebeth</hi> did not ſhew much Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion neither, in the Synagogue; but ſhe is young, and perhaps ſhe is not in her heart a <hi>Jew,</hi> who can tell!</q>
            </p>
            <pb n="118" facs="tcp:66367:62"/>
            <p>As he went home, he pulled out <hi>Abigals</hi> Picture, and often looked upon it; and comparing the Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture of <hi>Joſebeth</hi> that he carried in his heart, with that other which he carried in his hand; he found in the firſt an Air of Sincerity and Conſtancy, which the laſt did no way promiſe: But on the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry a Phyſiognomy that appear'd with ſomething of lightneſs and falſeneſs, which indeed was the true Character of <hi>Abigal.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The night that brings reſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der its ſoft Wings, to all the World, brought none to <hi>Villeneufe;</hi> for the agitation of his own thoughts would not ſuffer him to take any. For the Paſſion which he had for <hi>Joſebeth,</hi> which his heart told him was very different from the former amuſements of gallantry which he had, the difficulties he ſaw to op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe his deſires, and yet the hopes that ſhe her ſelf had ſo plainly
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:66367:62"/>given him, of poſſeſſing her in the ways of honour; all this together raiſed a confuſion in his mind, and overſpread it with a darkneſs, thicker than that the night was wrapt in. Above all, he was cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elly troubled about the meaning of one part of <hi>Wanbergues</hi> Letter. <q>'Tis moſt certain, <hi>ſaid he,</hi> that this Raſcal of a Husband would fain be rid of <hi>Joſebeth,</hi> that he might have liberty to marry <hi>Abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gal!</hi> But how can I be ſure they will ſtop at deſires only? for they have neither of them over much ſcruples of Conſcience, and therefore they may eaſily go on from unjuſt deſires to unjuſt acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. In a word, 'tis a <hi>Jew</hi> that hates his Wife, and writes to his Miſtreſs of deſigns that he has to gain her: What can thoſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns be; and if he ſhould really go on to execute any of them on <hi>Joſebeth,</hi> which ſhe might poſſibly
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:66367:63"/>prevent by having notice of them from me, and ſo periſh by my fault, I could not in my own death find a conſolation for hers.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Being overcome with this fear, he took <hi>Abigals</hi> Picture and Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers, when it was time to go to <hi>Joſebeth.</hi> 
               <q>Well, tell me, <hi>ſaid that lovely Woman, when ſhe ſaw him,</hi> is it not true that a little abſence does no injury to Love, when it is ſuch as it ought to be.</q>
               <q>I confeſs, Madam, he anſwered, that a ſhort ſeparation can work no change in a heart that loves truly; but 'tis as true, that all that while that heart injoys no quiet; and if it ſhould laſt long, it could have no joy: For there is this difference betwixt a Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band and a Lover, that the laſt looks upon every diſtance, as a danger he runs of loſing his hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs, which every thing threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ens in his abſence: Whereas the
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:66367:63"/>other, whoſe buſineſs is already done, makes him more deſirable by his abſence; and therefore makes a Journey on purpoſe, to bring back the conjugal affection more enflamed.</q>
               <q>But, <hi>ſays Joſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth,</hi> you do not conſider, that when the Eyes, the Mouth, and the Ears are not taken up with the Object before them, the flame, that elſe would be divided into thoſe ſeveral quarters, is all united in the Heart, and burns there ſo much the ſtronger: You may call it <hi>Singularity,</hi> if you pleaſe, but I ſhould beſt like ſo to order Love, that deſires and impatiencies ſhould follow plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures and injoyments.</q>
               <q>I know not, Madam, <hi>ſaid Villeneufe,</hi> if the frequent occaſions Monſieur <hi>Wanbergue</hi> takes to abſent him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, produce thoſe good effects be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt you, that you ſeem to deſire and commend: But this I know,
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:66367:64"/>that you are nor the Perſon whoſe abſence he mourns, but that there is another in the world, whoſe company he deſires much more than yours.</q> And at theſe words he pulled out the Picture, and the Papers, which <hi>Joſebeth</hi> took with a great Concern.</p>
            <p>The firſt Letter ſhe read, was that her Husband had writ, and ſaw there with ſome ſatisfaction the teſtimony he gave her of li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving retired, and never ſtirring from home. But when ſhe came to that part of the Letter, that ſpake, of her being pleaſed with the deſigns he had to gain her, ſhe fell into a great paſſion; and, as 'tis natural to ſuſpect the greateſt Crimes in people for whom one has an averſion, ſhe immediately believed, that her Husband intend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to poyſon her, if <hi>Abigal</hi> would have him. Afterwards ſhe read <hi>Abigal</hi>'s Anſwer; and when ſhe
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:66367:64"/>had done, <hi>See,</hi> ſaid ſhe, <hi>the ſtile of that ill Woman: But ſhe does not appear ſo wicked as her Lover; and I do not find that ſhe would make uſe of the Power that Traytor gives her over my Life, though one can't be ſure what her thoughts are, becauſe her Letter is not finiſhed, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps the Sentence for my Death would be the laſt thing ſhe would have writ.</hi> There was yet one Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per more to read, but ſhe was ſo angry, ſhe could not mind it; it was the Cypher, and the way of ſpeaking by Signs; and <hi>Villeneufe</hi> had a great Curioſity to know the Author, and therefore preſented it again to <hi>Joſebeth,</hi> deſiring her to read it. As ſoon as ever ſhe ſaw it, ſhe cryed out, <hi>Oh my fine Saint, he was fit to make one in this Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny. 'Tis that Hypocrite</hi> Rabby Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſſas, <hi>who thought, it ſeems, to find more favour with</hi> Abigal <hi>than he had with me. And it was very true,
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:66367:65"/>for that old Raſcal, that endeavour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to comfort himſelf for the loſs of</hi> Joſebeth, <hi>found no body in his Flock ſo fit to drive away his melancholly, as</hi> Abigal. <hi>But becauſe her looſe way of living made it ſcandalous, for a Man of</hi> Manaſſas <hi>Profeſſion, to viſit her with that aſſiduity that was requiſite for his deſign, they agreed to ſpeak to one another before the World with Signs, which that Holy Doctor was to make a Liſt of; which he had accordingly done, and ſent her, that day that ſhe went to keep the Feaſt of Tabernacles, that ſo ſhe might make uſe of the leiſure time ſhe ſhould have in the Syna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gogue, to ſtudy ſo devout a Leſſon.</hi> So horrible a profanation of the Myſteries of Religion, by the chief Perſon concerned to obſerve and celebrate them, gave an occaſion to <hi>Villeneufe</hi> to perſwade <hi>Joſebeth</hi> to leave the Communion of ſuch Hypocrites, and come over to the
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:66367:65"/>Chriſtian Religion. <hi>You ſpeak well for your own intereſt,</hi> ſaid ſhe, <hi>if it be true, that you love me as much as you pretend, for if I turned Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian, 'twould be in your power to marry me, if you deſired it. Ville<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neufe</hi> that never heard of any ſuch Cuſtom, threw himſelf at her feet, and begg'd her to tell him how that could be. <q>There is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing more uſual, <hi>ſaid Joſebeth,</hi> than that practiſe, which is uſed both in <hi>Flanders</hi> and <hi>Holland;</hi> and the manner of it is this, When a Jewiſh Woman has a mind to turn Chriſtian, ſhe cites her Husband before the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate, that he may there declare, if he has a mind to make himſelf a Chriſtian, and he has eight days given him to conſider what he will do; and in that time, he and his Wife live apart: If at the end of that time he forſake the Jewiſh Religion, the Marriage ſtands
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:66367:66"/>good; but if he continue obſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate, to live and die a Jew, his Wife then proteſts ſhe can't live with him, for fear of her Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence; and then ſhe has paid her back the Portion ſhe brought him, and is ſuffered to marry where ſhe pleaſes. 'Tis but a year ago, that the ſame thing happened in <hi>Amſterdam,</hi> to a fine Woman of the Jewiſh Nation, called <hi>Dora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zith,</hi> that afterwards married the Lieutenant Colonel of the Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of <hi>Inderſum.</hi> In a word, <hi>ſaid Joſebeth,</hi> 'tis the only way in which you ſhall obtain me, and 'twas this I meant, when I ſpoke confuſedly to you, in the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of our Acquaintance.</q> 
               <hi>Vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leneufe</hi> touched to the Heart with the Propoſition <hi>Joſebeth</hi> had made him, kiſſed her Hand which ſhe gave him, and ſwore to Heaven, that he would eſteem more than all the World the honour to poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſs
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:66367:66"/>
               <hi>Joſebeth. But Madam,</hi> ſaid he, <hi>what if</hi> Wanbergue <hi>ſhould have a fancy to turn Chriſtian too: Oh, there is no fear of that,</hi> ſaid Joſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth, <hi>and would I were as ſure of your Conſtancy to me, as I am of his to the Jewiſh Religion, for which his zeal is very great; nay, I believe he has ſo much averſion for me, that he would be glad of my Converſion, that ſo he might be left at liberty to mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry another.</hi> 
               <q>But Madam, all the <hi>Rabbins,</hi> and <hi>Manaſſas</hi> that has ſo great an Authority, do you think they will be quiet, and do no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to hinder us? They are Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>believers, and Unbelievers that you have injured, and do you think they will not try all ways to moleſt you?</q>
               <q>For that, <hi>ſaid Joſebeth,</hi> many things are to be anſwered. Firſt, this is a Cuſtom and Law eſtabliſhed, that can no more be queſtioned: And then you know, that in this Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:66367:67"/>there is no violence or diſorder ſuffer'd, and though all Religions are here permitted, yet the Jews are the leaſt favoured by the Publick of any other: And then, you little know what ſort of people <hi>Manaſſas</hi> and his Brethren are, if you think they will concern themſelves out of zeal, to keep me in their Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: Alas, 'tis Policy not Devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion governs them, and they aim at nothing but their Intereſt. If people of ordinary condition come to them, for the expound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and interpreting the Law, they declare it in its utmoſt ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gour, that ſo they may get the Reputation of Preciſe and Holy Men; but if men of Quality want another Expoſition, they can explain it quite another way, that ſo they may maintain them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves by their Authority and Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour. 'Tis the ſame in matter of
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:66367:67"/>Reputation; for though a Man have neither real honour, nor honeſty, and a Woman give juſt occaſion to all the Town to talk of her, provided they go to the Feaſt of Tabernacles, and hold a Bough devoutly in their hands; if they do but ſpeak well of their Spiritual Leaders, and ſay they deſerve eſteem and reſpect, all is well; their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences ſhall be quiet, and our Rabbins will ſend them to Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, without ever changing their Life on Earth: And on the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſide, if one does not blindly admire all they Preach, and take care to court their favour, one ſhall be cryed down for the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Atheiſt in the World. All this is plain, in their carriage to me and <hi>Abigal.</hi> Becauſe I never ſhew'd over much care to pleaſe them, they have done all they can to injure me, but to no purpoſe,
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:66367:68"/>becauſe my way of living has given them no occaſion to faſten on; however they have often ſaid, that the ſmall reſpect I paid the Prieſts, was a certain ſign I had no Religion in my heart: And as it lies in their power to make ſome ſort of diſtinction in the Synagogue, they have there taken occaſion ſometimes to ſhew their little ſpleen; but ſeeing that I laughed at their little tricks, they were pleaſed to find that <hi>Wanber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gue</hi> had ſome Intrigue, and have done what they could to favour her and him, on purpoſe to vex me: Nay, they let me know, that one of the Rabbins themſelves, <hi>Marezul</hi> by Name, had been em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed to carry Love-Letters be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt them. On the other ſide, <hi>Abigal</hi> living in that liberty ſhe takes, has yet ſo much of their favour, that upon all occaſions they juſtifie her actions, and cry
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:66367:68"/>her up for a Woman of Piety. Whiles ſhe gets ſo much indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence by ſubmitting to their pride; ſhe calls them her Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles, and adores their Perſons, kiſſes the bottom of their Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and often ſends them conſiderable Preſents.</q>
               <q>And my treacherous Husband too, <hi>ſays Joſebeth,</hi> for the ſame reaſon, ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves the ſame method, to gain thoſe Mercenary Wretches. He often invites them to Dinner, and then I muſt take an extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary care to treat them ſplen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>didly. And the other day, <hi>Wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bergue</hi> and <hi>Abigal,</hi> agreed to ſend a Preſent of fine Cloath to <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſſas,</hi> that he, and the reſt, might appear handſomly dreſt at the Feaſt of Tabernacles: ſo that with theſe Precautions, both he and ſhe live how they pleaſe, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the protection of theſe baſe Hypocrites.</q>
               <q>Seeing 'tis ſo, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam,
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:66367:69"/>
                  <hi>ſaid Villeneufe,</hi> why do you make any ſcruple to leave a Party, where there is neither Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, nor Religion, and to come into a better way?</q>
               <q>I have had thoughts ſo to do, a great while, <hi>ſaid Joſebeth,</hi> and the firſt Edu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation I had in the Chriſtian Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, gave me a great Averſion for theſe Rabbins.</q>
            </p>
            <p>At laſt they both agreed that <hi>Villeneufe</hi> ſhould, next day, go a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way with all haſte to <hi>Louvain,</hi> that he might have the Opinion of the Doctors of his own Religion about marrying <hi>Joſebeth;</hi> and that in the mean time, <hi>Joſebeth</hi> ſhould live with her Husband, as ſhe had done before.</p>
            <p>As <hi>Villeneuſe</hi> was on the way, he could do nothing but admire the goodneſs of <hi>Joſebeth,</hi> which ſhe had ſhewn him in this laſt Converſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: For according to the Rules of a great Paſſion, he ſhould have been
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:66367:69"/>ſo tranſported with the offer ſhe made him of marrying her, that all his Reaſon and Wit, ſhould have been given up intirely to his Joy: he ought not to have thought of any thing but that Felicity, and having once got his Miſtreſſes word, not have troubled his head with think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of other Obſtacles. And yet, inſtead of ſuch an obliging Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſport, he had coldneſs enough to reflect on the offer ſhe made him, and to propoſe a thouſand difficul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties againſt his own happineſs; in a word, he looked as if he was ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king a bargain, and that he would be aſſured of all things before<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hand. A proceeding that had no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in it, of gratitude, or tender love, and yet <hi>Joſebeth</hi> had had ſweetneſs, and goodneſs enough to bear it patiently, and calmly anſwer all his Objections. However, he thought, that in all this he had done his duty; and in reality, he had
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:66367:70"/>in this ſhewed the greateſt token of his kindneſs that was poſſible. <hi>I have now,</hi> ſaid he, <hi>experiment<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the difference there is, betwixt a love of Gallantry, and a love of Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage; for formerly, whenever I in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged my ſelf in a Ladies ſervice, 'twas to follow my preſent inclina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, without ever troubling my ſelf with the conſequence that might happen. But now I well found by another temper of my heart, that</hi> Joſebeth, <hi>my lovely</hi> Joſebeth, <hi>gave me Chains that were to tye me all my Life; and the happineſs of poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſing her appeared ſo unlikely, that I could not but diſpute, to be aſſured of its reality.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>With theſe thoughts he got to <hi>Louvain,</hi> and immediately made his caſe known to the Doctors there; who, in a Writing under their hands, gave their Opinion, that the Marriage of a converted <hi>Jew,</hi> whoſe Husband would continue
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:66367:70"/>ſtill in that Superſtition, with a Chriſtian man, was good and va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lid: They brought ſeveral Citati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons out of the Canon Law; and at the bottom Sign'd it,
<q>Siunich. Wauverne. Loyens.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Thoſe good men would not let <hi>Ville neufe</hi> go, without taking occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to give him wholeſome in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions, telling him, that Marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age was not ordained to pleaſe the Luſt of the Fleſh, but that he ought to propoſe to himſelf a higher and Nobler End, without which— But our Lover having got that which he came for; cut off that Grave Diſcourſe with a Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent Bow he made them; and ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king this Declaration which the Secretary of the Colledge, M. <hi>Nau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>landt</hi> gave him, he went to take Horſe, to go back as faſt as he came. But his return was not ſo
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:66367:71"/>ſoon as he intended; for as he was going away, he was ſtopped by an Officer, and ſome Souldiers, and carried away Priſoner to the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernour of the Caſtle, <hi>Dom Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riques de Carrero.</hi> That <hi>Spaniard,</hi> whom ſuch a Place made very proud, uſed <hi>Villeneufe</hi> at firſt very rudely; letting him know in an unhandſome manner, that he took him for a Spy, as indeed <hi>Dom Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riques</hi> was informed that he really was; for the War then continued betwixt <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Spain,</hi> and the people of <hi>Louvain</hi> had an extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary hatred for the <hi>French,</hi> ever ſince the Marſhal <hi>de Breze</hi> beſieged their City, who, after having ſpent a great deal of time, and a great many men, deſtroyed all their Country, out of rage, that he was forced to raiſe his Siege: So that having taken notice of <hi>Villeneufe,</hi> as he went up and down the Town about his buſineſs, with an air, and
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:66367:71"/>way that made them take him for a <hi>French-man:</hi> Thoſe who had no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elſe to do, were glad to do a <hi>French-man</hi> an ill turn, and went and told the Governour, that he looked like a dangerous Man. 'Twas to no purpoſe that he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plained in <hi>Dutch</hi> of the injury that they did him, for the Governour with a <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Gravity, without ſo much as hearing him, made a ſign they ſhould carry him away; and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way they had him into a Chamber that was not extraordinarily well furniſhed. The Officer that had the charge of him, ſtayed with him in the Room to entertain him, and told him at laſt, that though his Excellence was moſt exact in do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his Duty, yet he knew how to treat Gentlemen. The Priſoner preſently ſmelt what he would be at, and therefore took out a Gold Watch he had about him, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired him he would preſent that to
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:66367:72"/>his Excellence, as a Token of his Reſpect. He thought from the firſt that it would coſt him ſomething to get out of their Clutches; but he thought now, after this Preſent, he ſhould quickly have his liberty: And that thought making him a little more eaſie, he could not but laugh at the Title of Excellence given to <hi>Dom Henriques,</hi> who was indeed a Gentleman; but of thoſe Gentlemen, that after having ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved a long time, in recompence have the Government of ſome Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon in the <hi>Low-Countries;</hi> where minding nothing but to ſcrape to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether a little Money, they turn Pyrates on the Land, and make Slaves of all that come near them, and all for the ſecurity of the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate. This Gentleman had extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary reaſon for what he did, which was, the ſmallneſs of the Pay, both for himſelf, his Souldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, and for the repairs of the
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:66367:72"/>Works which fell down every day: ſo that <hi>Dom Henriques</hi> looked upon the Impriſonment of <hi>Villeneufe</hi> as an extraordinary good Fortune, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved to uſe it accordingly.</p>
            <p>Our Priſoner was much ſurpri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed, when the Officer came back, and told him, his Excellence had accepted the Watch; that he was going to <hi>Bruſſels,</hi> and promiſed him on the word of a Gentleman, he would do what he could in his behalf with the Council of State. <hi>How,</hi> ſaid <hi>Villeneufe,</hi> almoſt mad, <hi>with the Council of State! what a buſineſs you</hi> Spaniards <hi>make of no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing? You</hi> French-men, ſaid the Officer very gravely, taking him by the hand, <hi>are too haſty, and you ought to render thanks to his Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, for the care he takes of you: For I had not yet told you,</hi> Seignior, continued he, ſmiling ſo much as ſhewed his naſty teeth, <hi>that his Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellence has given Order to have
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:66367:73"/>you removed to a better Chamber, and be permitted the uſe of the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle to walk in. I have ſeen a great many Priſoners of State in my time, but I never ſaw any have ſo much favour ſhewn them at firſt, as you.</hi> Whiles the Officer was talking on this manner, <hi>Villeneufe</hi> walked up and down the Room, ſtamping with his feet, looking up to Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, and raving like a man out of his Wits; ſo that he only heard the laſt words the Officer ſaid, to whom he anſwered with a wild look, <hi>You have a mind to make me mad with your favours, and your Excellencies, that are as ridiculous one as the other. Zounds,</hi> ſaid he, quite diſtracted, thinking to lay his hand on his Sword, forgetting they had took it from him, becauſe it had a Silver Handle. The thought that he was diſarmed, and a Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoner, ſoftned him a little; he turn'd away from the Officer with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:66367:73"/>ſpeaking a word, and went to the Window in ſuch a horrible me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancholly, that he eat nothing all day. At night they carried him into another Chamber, a little neater, that joyned to <hi>Dom Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riques</hi> Apartment: But that Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commodation did him no good; he could think of nothing but <hi>Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſebeth;</hi> and when he conſidered, that ſhe might have an ill opinion of his ſtay, he had not patience to endure that thought, and he had rather have died, than have lain under her ſuſpitions; for he was to have been abſent but four days, and now he could ſee no end of his ſtay. This made him rail anew a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> whom he ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver had much loved; and he came to make particular Curſes againſt <hi>Dom Henriques.</hi> He remembred to have read in the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Hiſtory, that ever ſince the <hi>Moors</hi> left <hi>Spain,</hi> there ſtayed behind them a
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:66367:74"/>Race of <hi>Jews,</hi> that took Baptiſm that they might injoy their Eſtates, and Offices; they call them <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranes,</hi> who for all their Chriſtiani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, from Father to Son, keep a hid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den zeal for their Religion. <hi>With<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out doubt,</hi> ſaid he, <hi>this curſed Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernour is one of that Race, and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving found my buſineſs hither, by my Papers which he has ſeized, he is inraged to find I have been the occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of Converting a</hi> Jew, <hi>and is reſolved to be revenged on me for the wrong I have done his falſe Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But after having given a little vent to his Paſſion, he began to caſt about how he might gain his liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; at laſt reſolved to ingage the Marqueſs of <hi>Trechateau,</hi> Grand Marſhal of <hi>Lorain,</hi> that was then at <hi>Bruſſels</hi> with Duke <hi>Charles.</hi> In his youth he had made a friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip with him in the Accademy, and though afterwards their inga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:66367:74"/>in different Intereſts had hinder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed them from having any Converſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, yet he hoped the Marſhal had not quite forgot him. And in that he was not deceived; for the Marſhal was generous, and ſo well employed the Credit of Duke <hi>Charles,</hi> that he obtained <hi>Villeneufe's</hi> liberty; 'twas not without leaving ſomething be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind him, and the Officer that had took his Sword at firſt, would needs change Swords with him, that he might, he ſaid, preſerve ſomething in memory of ſo fine a Gentleman. <hi>Villeneufe</hi> was fain to leave his own, which was of value, and had his in change, that had a handle looked like the Circles of a Sphere: 'twas with ſome difficulty too, that the <hi>Spaniard</hi> parted with it, for it had been kept in his Family ever ſince the Wars of <hi>Charles</hi> the fifth. <hi>Ville<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neufe,</hi> that feared ſome other trick, made all the haſte he could to get away, and reckoned it for a good
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:66367:75"/>fortune to part with them at ſo ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie a rate. He had been abſent from <hi>Amſterdam</hi> ten days; and that long ſeparation that he could not foreſee at parting, gave him the greater impatience to ſee <hi>Joſebeth;</hi> and that impatience was increaſed, when his Man told him <hi>Solomoune</hi> had been two days together to ſee whether he was come back; and at that very inſtant the Nurſe came in, looking ſo ill that he could hardly know her: <hi>We are undone,</hi> ſaid ſhe, <hi>and</hi> Joſebeth <hi>is loſt.</hi> At theſe words, her ſighs ſtopt her breath, and her grief ſo ſeized her that ſhe could not ſpeak. <hi>Villeneufe,</hi> more ſtruck with that News than if it had been a Thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derbolt, as ſoon as ſhe was come to her ſelf, begg'd her to ſpeak plainer. <hi>Oh,</hi> ſaid ſhe, Joſebeth, <hi>our dear Miſtreſs</hi> Joſebeth, <hi>is now in the Power of the Rabbins, and they will certainly take away her life.</hi>
               <pb n="145" facs="tcp:66367:75"/>
               <q>But what is the matter, <hi>ſaid Ville<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neufe,</hi> what has ſhe done, for Gods ſake tell me what it is?</q> 
               <hi>You must know then,</hi> ſaid <hi>Solomoune,</hi> crying, and wiping her Eyes, <hi>that</hi> Wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bergue, <hi>as falſe as</hi> Joab, <hi>or, as you Chriſtians ſay, as falſe as</hi> Judas, <hi>took a fancy three days ago, to riſe out of his own Bed very early in the morning, to go to</hi> Joſebeth, <hi>contrary to his cuſtome, with a pretence of kindneſs and love, but in truth for a worſe end. She, poor Creature, that was tired with your abſence, and found her only comfort in hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing before her Eyes the tokens of your friendſhip, had on, by ill fortune, the Smock where you had writ your Verſes; for it was far enough from her thoughts, that her Husband, that had paſſed ſix Months without ever troubling her with his Careſſes, ſhould that night have a fancy to play the Gallant: So that Brute, leaping in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Bed, and flinging off the Cloaths,
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:66367:76"/>ſaw ſomething writ upon her Smock, he would have drawn the Curtains to ſee what 'twas; but ſhe hinder'd him, which was the worſt of all: for</hi> Wanbergue, <hi>gueſſing by her reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance that there was ſomething of importance to be diſcovered, would needs ſee it, and was ſo angry, that he was like to beat her for going to conceal it. After having tired her with ſtrugling, he did not only read your Verſes, but pulled the Smock off her back, and carried it immediate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to</hi> Manaſſas, <hi>to conſult what was fit to be done. You may gueſs, if that curſed Rabbin was not overjoyed to have in his hands an opportunity to be revenged on</hi> Joſebeth. <hi>Yeſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day he called an Aſſembly of the chief of the Synagogue; but all their Counſels are kept ſo ſecret, that 'tis impoſſible to know what was done there, only thus much, that</hi> Joſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth <hi>muſt appear before them again this Afternoon. They are Devils,</hi>
               <pb n="147" facs="tcp:66367:76"/>ſaid the Nurſe, <hi>without Conſcience, and Honour, and you ſhall ſee that they will put her to death:</hi> and then ſhe fell into ſo cruel a paſſion, that they thought it would kill her.</p>
            <p>All that the Nurſe had ſaid was very true; and the <hi>Jews</hi> took an extraordinary care to conceal the buſineſs, that it might not be Town<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talk, for never was there ſuch an occaſion for railery; and that hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen'd by the malice of <hi>Maneſſas,</hi> who being reſolved to ruine <hi>Joſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth,</hi> brought out her Smock into the middle of the Synagogue, in the preſence of all the Doctors and Levites, who were to read the Verſes: One of them held up the Smock, and read the Verſes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loud.</p>
            <p>Afterwards they gave the Smock about from one to another, very gravely to be looked on. The Old eſt of them could ſcarce keep in his laughter; and when it came
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:66367:77"/>to <hi>Rabbin Recabith,</hi> who was very Ancient, <hi>'Twas never heard of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore,</hi> ſaid he, <hi>that ſuch a ſhame fell upon a Daughter of</hi> Iſrael. Every one ſaid ſomething, and it was pleaſant enough to ſee forty grave Doctors in their Gowns, all peer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing upon a Smock, with as great Solemnity, as the people did at <hi>Rome,</hi> when the Veſt of <hi>Julius Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſar</hi> was expoſed to their view by <hi>Anthony.</hi> Their reſolution was to have <hi>Joſebeth</hi> come before them the next Afternoon, which was the day that <hi>Villeneufe</hi> came to Town. He was mad to think he had occaſioned ſuch a misfortune to his Miſtreſs; he curſed <hi>Wanber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gue</hi> and <hi>Manaſſas</hi> above all the reſt, and ſwore ſolemnly to make them pay dearly for it, if any thing happened to <hi>Joſebeth. But,</hi> ſaid he to the Nurſe, <hi>is there no way to ſpeak with</hi> Joſebeth? <hi>Alas,</hi> ſaid ſhe, <hi>I know not where 'tis they keep
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:66367:77"/>her, nor can tell where 'tis ſhe is to appear this Afternoon, which they keep ſecret, for fear they ſhould be diſturbed in their judgment. I have heard,</hi> ſays Villeneufe, <hi>that the</hi> Jews <hi>have no power of Judicature among the</hi> Chriſtians, <hi>nor power to put any one to death: That's true,</hi> ſaid ſhe, <hi>but yet they are ſuffered the liberty of exerciſing a great ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of their Ceremonies, and ſome of their Ceremonies cannot be perform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed without paſſing judgment; and I underſtand this now in hand, is of that kind; And ſo under pretence that the Cuſtoms of our Law muſt be fulfilled, the Sentence of the</hi> Rab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bins <hi>muſt be executed; and if they go farther than they ought, they will come off for a good ſum of Money: In the mean time, a good Fine does not bring back the dead. You are in the right,</hi> ſaid Villeneufe, <hi>there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore let us try all ways to prevent thoſe Butchers. I have a Friend a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:66367:78"/>them,</hi> ſays the Nurſe, <hi>who does not hate</hi> Joſebeth, <hi>as the others do, and he will give me notice, I hope, as ſoon as he can. But were it not better for me to go immediately to the Magiſtrate, and make com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint,</hi>—ſaid Villeneufe. <hi>No, by no means,</hi> ſaid Solomoune, <hi>for 'tis</hi> Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſebeths <hi>advantage, that they can never convince her of any Intrigue, or lay any Man to her Charge, and this way you would diſcover all, and give the</hi> Rabbins <hi>a juſt occaſion to triumph. Oh God,</hi> ſaid he, <hi>the Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes on the Smock, do they not give ſuſpitions enough: They are but ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpitions,</hi> ſaid the Nurſe, <hi>and ſhe has wit enough to take them off.</hi> 'Tis true, the Verſes made the <hi>Jews</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve there were ſome ſecret Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lantry, and therefore they feared that ſome Party might be made to take <hi>Joſebeth</hi> our of their hands. <hi>Wanbergue</hi> cover'd the hate he had for his Wife, under the great re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:66367:78"/>he was bound to bear the Law, and hoped by that means, either her Death, or a Divorce, would give him liberty to make a new choice. He deceived himſelf for all that in his hopes, for <hi>Abigal</hi> had not ſo much deſire to marry him, as ſhe had, and cared for no other ingagement with him, but that of a great Friendſhip. 'Twas difficult to gueſs at the cauſe of his Inconſtancy, which was the preſent misfortune of <hi>Joſebeth;</hi> for the Envy that <hi>Abigal</hi> bore to the Reputation and Beauty of <hi>Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſebeth,</hi> made her chiefly ſollicitous to rob her of her Husbands heart; and now that ſhe ſaw her hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled, ſhe ceaſed to be her Rival, her vanity being ſatisfied with her Enemies fall: But the malice of <hi>Manaſſas,</hi> and the other <hi>Rabbins,</hi> was not ſo eaſily ſatisfied, for they looked on her as a perſon that had never reſpected them as they deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red,
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:66367:79"/>and therefore reſolved to make uſe of this occaſion to ruine her, who was like to have a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt for them as long as ſhe li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved. However, to make a ſhew of Religion and Juſtice, they had locked up <hi>Joſebeth</hi> in a place which the Magiſtrates had given them leave to aſſemble in: 'twas a kind of great Warehouſe, that held a great deal of their Goods, where they uſed alſo ſometimes to meet about their Affairs: There are ſome Chambers there, where they uſe to puniſh the offenders of their Law with great ſecreſie, that they may not give occaſion of ſcandal to the Chriſtians. Here 'twas they met to conſult about <hi>Joſebeth,</hi> whom they ſent for from the Chamber where they had kept her. She came in to them with a ſerene Air, and an aſſured Counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, behaving her ſelf with the courage belonging to Innocence.
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:66367:79"/>They ſhewed her her Smock, and asked her what thoſe Verſes meant, and who 'twas made them, and why ſhe would not let her Husband ſee them? She called up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>Wanbergue,</hi> who was there, to witneſs to the truth of what ſhe was going to ſay; and then an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered them very calmly, that the coldneſs of her Husband, and the little enjoyment ſhe had had of his Company, made her ſeek diverſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in reading of Romances, which ſerved to fill her fancy; and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving ſome of thoſe kind of Adven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures in her head, ſhe had writ thoſe Verſes that were proper e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to amuſe a Perſon of her Age. That ſhe had made thoſe Verſes only to pleaſe her ſelf, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving as much Poetry as that came to: And ſhe had done what ſhe could to keep her Husband from reading them, that he might not jeer her about them, as he uſed to
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:66367:80"/>do. She confirmed her Innocence by the retired life ſhe had always led, and dar'd them all to name the Man with whom they could reproach her. <hi>Where is my Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lant,</hi> ſaid ſhe, <hi>what is his name, where does he live, that I may ſee him, and then I will ask no favour? But if there be no ſuch thing, then let juſtice be done me on thoſe that take occaſion from a fooliſh and harm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs fancy, to accuſe me of falſeneſs and treachery. We do not condemn you for any thing,</hi> ſaid Manaſſas, who was Preſident in that Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly, <hi>but you ought not to be angry, if being in doubt, we follow the preſcriptions of the Law in ſuch oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions. Rabbin,</hi> ſaid ſhe, <hi>you know beſt, if</hi> Joſebeth <hi>be a perſon of Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue or no.</hi> He feared ſome ſuch an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, and therefore was gone a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout to take the Voices, which all agreed, that <hi>Joſebeth</hi> ſhould take the Waters of Jealouſie. When
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:66367:80"/>they had pronounced that Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence, ſhe ſat down quietly to ſee the Execution; which according to their preſent Cuſtom was on this manner: If any man was jealous of his Wife, he was to come be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Prieſts, to tell them the reaſons of his jealouſie; and if they were judged ſufficient, he was ſuffer'd to try the virtue of his Wife in the preſence of the chief of their Nation; the way was this, a Prieſt wrote upon a piece of Parchment theſe words, <hi>Let the Woman who has been falſe to her Husband periſh;</hi> and when the Woman had conſented to the Curſe, they ſhaved off from the Parchment theſe written words, and gave her the ſhavings to drink in a Glaſs of Water, with ſo won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derful a ſucceſs, that if the Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man was innocent, that Drink on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly increaſed her Beauty; but if ſhe were guilty, as ſoon as ſhe had
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:66367:81"/>drank the Water, ſhe felt moſt hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible pains all over her Body, her Belly and her Thighs ſwelled, and ſo ſhe dyed in a diſmal manner.</p>
            <p>Thus it was when anciently this Law flouriſhed in <hi>Judea;</hi> but ſince that Law has been aboliſhed by the Maker of it, all thoſe Won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders ceaſe, and there remains no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but a Curſe on that unhap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py People.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Manaſſas</hi> knew very well that alteration; for the Rabbins of <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lan</hi> and <hi>Lisbon,</hi> confeſs that the Waters of Jealouſie have loſt their virtue. They do indeed attribute this loſs, to the Diſperſion of their Nation, and not to the Abolition of their Worſhip; imagining that if they were again eſtabliſhed in <hi>Judea,</hi> that myſterious Water would have the ſame effect now that it had formerly. But they do own, that in all places elſe thoſe Waters do not work as formerly.
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:66367:81"/>Notwithſtanding <hi>Manaſſas,</hi> who was reſolved to make thoſe Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters ſerve his deſign, maintained their virtue, and backed his opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on with a many reaſonings, and Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples, which made all the other Rabbins join with him in the ſame judgment. The Water then was made ready; and when that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viliſh Monſter had took the Glaſs, to ſay over it certain Prayers; du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring which, the other Rabbins held their Eyes fixed on the Ground, he put into it a little Powder, which one could not diſcern from the ſhavings of Parchment and Ink, that were in the Glaſs, and thick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned the Water.</p>
            <p>As ſoon as the Prayers, and all the Ceremony was over, they let <hi>Joſebeth</hi> come in: The indignati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſhe had to ſee her ſelf reduced to that extremity, brought a red into her Cheeks, that ſo raiſed her beauty, that thoſe wretched Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:66367:82"/>could do nothing but look on her. <hi>Manaſſas,</hi> with a counterfeit compaſſion, exhorted her not to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe her ſelf to a certain danger, if ſhe knew her ſelf guilty; but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to gain the favour of God and Men, by a ſincere Repentance. That impudence of <hi>Manaſſas</hi> took away <hi>Joſebeths</hi> patience; <hi>Give me, Hypocrite,</hi> ſaid ſhe, <hi>give me the Glaſs; this proof of my honour is more agreeable to me than that o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther you lately put me to.</hi> And at that inſtant they heard a terrible cry at the Door. However, ſhe went on, holding the Glaſs in her hand; <hi>Then you all agree,</hi> ſaid ſhe, <hi>that this Drink will make the Adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſs dye, but that it hurts no body elſe.</hi> To which they having all aſſented, by a nod of their head; ſhe asked for another Glaſs; and having poured the Water out of one into the other, ſeveral times, that it might the better mix; ſhe
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:66367:82"/>put half of it into one Glaſs, and half into another, and preſented them both to <hi>Manaſſas: Seeing this Water,</hi> ſaid ſhe, <hi>hurts none but the Adultereſs, pray let us drink it together, and take which Glaſs you pleaſe.</hi> 
               <q>That which you de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire, <hi>ſaid</hi> Manaſſas, <hi>very gravely,</hi> would alter the order of the Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remony, and that we can by no means conſent to; for we muſt not paſs our ſet bounds.</q> 
               <hi>You can,</hi> ſaid Joſebeth, <hi>more eaſily paſs a Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſtrade of Iron, than any Ceremony of your Law.</hi> At theſe words the Rabbins looked ſtrangely at one a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother; and <hi>Manaſſas,</hi> to divert them, roſe up again to take their Voices upon this new Matter; when the cry was ſo violent at the Door that one of them went to ſee what was the matter, and finding it was only a Woman, that ſaid ſhe had ſomething of great conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence to tell them, he let her
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:66367:83"/>in. <hi>Joſebeth</hi> quickly perceived it was <hi>Solomoune,</hi> with a Velvet Coat in her Lap, which ſo ſurpriſed <hi>Manaſſas,</hi> that he was ready to ſpeak down dead, not being able to ſpeak one word. <hi>Solomoune</hi> made uſe of his confuſion to beg leave of the Rabbins to ſpeak, who ſeeing an extraordinary concern in her Face, bid her declare her buſineſs. She threw down the Velvet Coat be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore them, to be examined like <hi>Joſebeth</hi>'s Smock, and then told them all the Adventure of <hi>Manaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſas</hi> the rainy night, with his paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the Baluſtrade, and leaving that Coat behind him, with ſo many Circumſtances, and ſuch an Air of truth, as was not to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſted: However, thoſe Rabbins would not ſeem to credit her, not to bring a diſhonour on their Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion; but yet <hi>Joſebeth</hi> had ſo much cauſe to ſuſpect the effects of <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſſa's</hi> hatred, that they agreed he
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:66367:83"/>ſhould drink the half of the Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. While they were on this de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liberation, <hi>Manaſſas</hi> retired, under pretence of praying, but indeed to conſider with himſelf what he was to do: At laſt he reſolved rather to hazard the loſs of his Life, than his Reputation; and having taken a Cordial he always uſed to carry about him, he came to them, ſaying, it was fit to uſe all ſort of Complaiſance: <q>You may ſee, <hi>ſaid he further, turning to Joſebeth,</hi> by my condeſcention, how little I have deſerved the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſation you have brought againſt me.</q> Inſtead of Anſwer, ſhe took both the Glaſſes, and gave them to <hi>Manaſſas</hi> to chuſe which he pleaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: He took off one, invoking e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven then, the God of <hi>Abraham, Iſaac,</hi> and <hi>Jacob.</hi> And afterwards <hi>Joſebeth</hi> drank off the other, and lifting her Glaſs up, as an Offering to Heaven, cryed out, <hi>Let the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:66367:84"/>be ſaved, and the guilty pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh;</hi> and ſo drank off the Water, which ſhe really believed was a Potion of Death. And ſhe was not deceived, though ſhe had no other ground for her ſuſpicion, than the hatred ſhe knew <hi>Manaſſas</hi> bore her, and that was enough, for there is no rage ſo great, as that of Love contemned.</p>
            <p>And now that wicked Man, who ever ſince the affront he received at the Baluſtrade of Iron, had been ſeeking an occaſion to be revenged, thought he had at laſt found one for his purpoſe; for as ſoon as ever <hi>Wanbergue</hi> had brought the buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs before him, he imagin'd the Waters of Jealouſie would ſerve to execute his malice, both effectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally, and ſecretly: And he had an extraordinary ſatisfaction, to think that <hi>Joſebeth</hi> ſhould receive her death from his hand, for he then reſolved to poyſon the Water he
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:66367:84"/>ſhould give her to drink: It had been difficult for another to have had a Poyſon that would not have ſhewed it ſelf, by changing the co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour and taſte of the Water; but he knew too well that Nation, that is famous for the ſecrets of Poyſon, to want one at his need. He wiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed only that <hi>Solomoune</hi> could have been obliged to pledge her Miſtreſs, that ſo he might not have left in the World a Witneſs able to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach him for his looſneſs.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Joſebeth</hi> had ſo much reaſon to fear this practice, that ſhe uſed the more vehemence to obtain the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der from the Rabbins that he might drink it with her, that ſo ſhe might draw that Hypocrite into the ſame Snare he had laid for her. Her Wit ended not there; for ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that <hi>Manaſſas,</hi> after having drunk the Water, diſmiſſed the Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembly, ſhe imagin'd it was chief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for himſelf, that he might in
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:66367:85"/>time go and take ſome powerful Antidote, and therefore did all ſhe could to detain the Company. <hi>'Tis very fit,</hi> ſaid ſhe, <hi>that I ſhould ſtay ſome time here before you, that you may judge of my Innocence by the ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects of your Water. That fearful Water,</hi> ſaid Manaſſas, <hi>does not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways work preſently, and ſometimes its Operation is ſuſpended by the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Goodneſs, that would give time for the Sinner to repent. I have heard though,</hi> ſaid <hi>Joſebeth,</hi> out of your Books, <hi>that as ſoon as the guilty Woman had taken it down, it immediately made her Countenance change, and her body ſwell.</hi> While ſhe was diſcourſing in this manner, they heard a terrible knocking at the door, and a mighty cry to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen it. At this noiſe they all turned their eyes towards <hi>Joſebeth,</hi> believing that noiſe was made for her ſake, and they began to fear the effects. <hi>You look pale,</hi> ſaid ſhe, <hi>is
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:66367:85"/>this your zeal for</hi> Zion, <hi>for which you ſo often proteſt that you would lay down your lives?</hi> But above all others, <hi>Manaſſas</hi> fear increaſed, knowing in his own Conſcience, the Merit of his Actions. The Rab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bin <hi>Eliezer,</hi> who was one of <hi>Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mounes</hi> Friends, had given her ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, that they intended to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn <hi>Joſebeth</hi> to drink the Waters of jealouſie, and that the Sentence would be immediately executed; which made the faithful Nurſe im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately run to ſome Chriſtian Ladies, who knew <hi>Joſebeth,</hi> beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging them to implore the aſſiſtance of the Magiſtrate, and do what they could to ſave ſo fine a Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man; and having given advice of what paſſed to <hi>Villeneufe,</hi> ſhe ran her ſelf to the Council of the <hi>Jews,</hi> endeavouring by accuſing <hi>Manaſſas,</hi> to gain time for her Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſes deliverance: And it was the Officers, thoſe Chriſtian La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:66367:86"/>had ſent, who with a crowd of people were at the door, which ſufficiently frighted the <hi>Jews,</hi> who had reaſon to believe <hi>Joſebeth</hi> would not ſave them from the fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of the people. In this apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, the <hi>Rabbins</hi> came to her, and beſought her to have pity on them. Thoſe ſubmiſſions which ſhe knew were extorted only by fear, did not work much upon her, and ſhe was not reſolved what to do: On one ſide ſhe ſaw the Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice of puniſhing ſuch Raſcals, and on the other the glory of par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doning thoſe whom ſhe had the power to deſtroy.</p>
            <p>In the mean time, the noiſe without increaſed, and ſeeing they did not open the door, a young Seaman that was more zealous than all the reſt, cryed, <hi>Break down the Doors;</hi> which was executed in a moment. That was no ſooner done, but the furious people broke
<pb n="167" facs="tcp:66367:86"/>in with a horrible diſorder, and in the Head of them that young Sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, that was <hi>Villeneufe</hi> diſgui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in that manner, to conceal the concern of his Love. He had a great Hatchet in his hand, ready to cut the <hi>Rabbins</hi> to pieces, if they had done any harm to <hi>Joſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth.</hi> She that knew him imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately through his diſguiſe, ſigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for joy, when ſhe ſaw him; and hearing the people cry out with a furious tone, <hi>Where are theſe</hi> Jews <hi>that would murder a</hi> Chriſtian, ſhe ran to the door of the Chamber where the <hi>Rabbins</hi> were, and hold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing her Arms acroſs it, that no bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy might go by her, <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> ſaid ſhe, <hi>that will be my Brethren very quickly, for Gods ſake forgive theſe poor Wretches; and being you are come hither for my ſake, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent your ſelves to ſee me triumph over them.</hi> The admiration they had of ſo much goodneſs, ſtopt
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:66367:87"/>their fury; and they that juſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore breathed nothing but threats and ruine to the <hi>Jews,</hi> ſent up no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to Heaven but praiſes of <hi>Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſebeth.</hi> But thoſe acclamations were redoubled, when after having beckned to them with her hand, that ſhe might be heard, ſaid aloud to her Husband, whom ſhe ſaw in the Crowd, <hi>Men here</hi> Wanbergue, <hi>I here declare to you in the preſence of all theſe good People, that I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce the</hi> Jewiſh <hi>Religion, and am reſolved to turn Chriſtian; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore conſider what you will do: for if you perſevere in your own Doctrine, I pretend, according to the Law, to have the Marriage diſſolved betwixt us.</hi> The <hi>Hollander</hi> half frighted out of his wits, ſaid, that ſhe ſhould ſuddenly know his mind; and ſo got out of the Crowd as faſt as he could, for fear the People ſhould do him a miſchief.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Joſebeth</hi> ought not to have made
<pb n="169" facs="tcp:66367:87"/>that Declaration any where, but before the Magiſtrates; but ſhe made ſo much the more haſte, to oblige <hi>Villeneufe,</hi> whom ſhe had before her Eyes: and in truth it was the only way to make amends for his ſufferings the eight days paſt. But his joy did not ſo take him up, as to make him neglect his buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; for ſeeing <hi>Wanbergue</hi> go out, fearing it might be to do ſomething againſt the Intereſt of <hi>Joſebeth,</hi> he went out too; but juſt at the Door, met the <hi>Sindike</hi> of the Town, with orders from the Magiſtrate to take <hi>Joſebeth</hi> into their protection: And as he was ſpeaking, the chief Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men of <hi>Amſterdam</hi> came alſo; they looked upon <hi>Joſebeth</hi> as one of the chiefeſt Ornaments of their Sex, and diſputed who ſhould have the pleaſure to entertain her: But at laſt Madam <hi>de Gere</hi> got the Victory, and carried <hi>Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſebeth</hi>
               <pb n="170" facs="tcp:66367:88"/>in triumph to her Houſe.</p>
            <p>The joy this ſtrange change cauſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed was not general; for while the Chriſtians ſung Victory, and ran from all parts to ſee <hi>Joſebeth:</hi> The <hi>Jews</hi> bewailed that day, as one of the moſt unfortunate they had ſeen of a great while. <hi>Joſebeth</hi> was not the only cauſe of their ſorrow; for it was increaſed by another loſs very conſiderable; and that was the death of <hi>Manaſſas,</hi> whom they looked on as a Pillar of their Church, and the glory of their Nation. He was taken with an ill fainting twice in their Meeting-Chamber, and they had got him to life again; and believing it was only occaſioned by the fright he was in for himſelf and the other Rabbins, they thought his ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs was nothing. But when the Clamour was over, and the Rabble gone; the Rabbins went
<pb n="171" facs="tcp:66367:88"/>to his Chair, where they thought he was aſleep, and found him dead: one cannot imagine the Lamenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions they made. And their af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection for him was ſo blind, that inſtead of thinking his death pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded from a Natural cauſe, they attributed it to his zeal for Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and the trouble he had for the affront it had ſuffered by <hi>Joſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>'Tis true, his death proceeded not from a Natural cauſe; and 'twas his zeal, but not for Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, that had cauſed it; for it was the Poyſon that he had pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared with ſo much warmth to give <hi>Joſebeth,</hi> that had killed him for all his Cordial: For when he firſt reſolved to deſtroy <hi>Joſebeth</hi> by the Waters of Jealouſie, he did ſo little think of ſharing the danger with her, that he had pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided no preſervative for himſelf:
<pb n="172" facs="tcp:66367:89"/>So that ſeeing himſelf ingaged in honour to make the tryal with her, he made uſe of the time he pretended to ſpend in Prayer, to take down an excellent Cordial he always carried about him, but it was no perfect Antidote againſt the power of Poyſon; however he thought that might ſecure him. But it fell out otherwiſe; for whether it were, that the Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dial was not of a quality to reſiſt that Poyſon, or that his Age had not the force to bear the Conflict, or that his fear kept the Cordial from working; 'tis evident that curſed Hypocrite gave himſelf that deadly blow that he intend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for another, and ended his days more quietly, and with leſs pain than he deſerved.</p>
            <p>And upon quite different ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compts, <hi>Joſebeth,</hi> that took the ſame water, had a different deſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny:
<pb n="173" facs="tcp:66367:89"/>For, having taken a juſt jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſie, by that part of <hi>Wanbergue</hi>'s Letter where he mentioned all deſigns of obtaining <hi>Abigal,</hi> that ſhe was in danger to be poyſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, ſhe had uſed her ſelf every morning to take a wonderful An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tidote: So that Youth being for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tified by ſo excellent a Remedy, eaſily overcame the Venom of the Poyſon.</p>
            <p>The joy ſhe had to ſee her ſelf out of danger by the Rabbins, and the Poyſon, was followed by ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, every whit as great; and that was the Declaration of <hi>Wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bergue,</hi> that being reſolved never to leave the Law of <hi>Moſes,</hi> he permitted her, being ſhe was turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Chriſtian, the liberty to chuſe another Husband: And afterward conſigned her all her Portion, and her Jewels, with greater honeſty than one would have expected.
<pb n="174" facs="tcp:66367:90"/>The impatience he had, to be at liberty too, to follow his inclinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, made him more eaſie, than otherwiſe he would have been: and this was a good effect of his love to <hi>Abigal,</hi> that had before pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced ſo many ill ones for <hi>Joſebeth.</hi> For his buſineſs was no ſooner ended with <hi>Joſebeth,</hi> but he made his pretenſion openly to <hi>Abigal,</hi> who yet was not much diſpoſed to ſubject her ſelf eternally to a Man, who before he had her, uſed her ſo imperiouſly as he did. <hi>How,</hi> ſaid ſhe, <hi>he does already find fault with my company, thinks I am too expenſive in my Cloaths and Houſe; if he has al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready ſo much Confidence, what will he do when he is my Maſter?</hi> She made theſe Reflexions, as ſoon as the misfortune of <hi>Joſebeth</hi> had de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed her Envy; and all joyned together, made her carry her ſelf
<pb n="175" facs="tcp:66367:90"/>very coldly to <hi>Wanbergue.</hi> But be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing governed only by her paſſion, and vanity having the chief ſway over her, when ſhe ſaw <hi>Joſebeth</hi> come out of her troubles with Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and Triumph, ſhe was poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed with her former Envy again; and ſeeing what Declaration <hi>Wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bergue</hi> had made, having her head filled with Emulation, ſhe thought it would be a great ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage to her to marry <hi>Wanber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gue,</hi> who choſe rather to have her for his Wife, than <hi>Joſebeth.</hi> To this reaſon that vanity made, ſhe added others of weight: For the Eſtate her other Husband left her, could not be taken out of <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterdam,</hi> becauſe if ſhe died with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Children, it was to be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed for the Publick Good of the <hi>Portugueze</hi> Nation: So that ſhe ſaw her ſelf confined to <hi>Amster<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam,</hi> without the liberty of paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing
<pb n="176" facs="tcp:66367:91"/>her life at <hi>Bruſſels,</hi> which ſhe ſo much deſired. And to ſtay a Widow all her life, was againſt all ſenſe; ſhe wanted a Husband to ſecure her Reputation, and that free humour which ſhe could by no means conſtrain; and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to marry, where could ſhe have ſuch a Husband as <hi>Wanber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gue?</hi> his Rank and Fortune could much better, than any other, maintain her in that great Splen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dour that ſhe had always lived in.</p>
            <p>All theſe Reaſons overcame the repugnance ſhe had at firſt to mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry <hi>Wanbergue,</hi> and made her ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept him for her Husband. This Marriage help'd to conſole the <hi>Rabbins</hi> for the loſs of <hi>Manaſſas,</hi> and <hi>Joſebeth,</hi> as well by the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſents the new married Couple made them, as by the feaſting at the Marriage, to which they were all invited.</p>
            <pb n="177" facs="tcp:66367:91"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Villeneufe</hi> did not poſſeſs <hi>Joſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth</hi> ſo ſoon; there being more Ceremony required to fore-run that happineſs: to accompliſh which, he was by his Friends in the Court of <hi>Bruſſels,</hi> invited thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, by the Arch-Duke <hi>Leopold,</hi> who then govern'd the <hi>Low-Countries.</hi> That Court was then full of Devotion, in imitation of the Arch-Duke: For that Prince, who was alſo, according to the Cuſtom in <hi>Germany,</hi> Commenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory Biſhop of <hi>Paſſaw,</hi> had inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>woven with Secular Splendour a mixture of Piety. He himſelf wore a little Band, and plain Cuffs, and ſaid every day his Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice with Father <hi>Chiflet,</hi> who had care of his Houſe as well as his Soul. This ſtrictneſs paſſed through all the Houſe, the very Pages being as exact to ſay their Prayer, as to do their other Exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſes.
<pb n="178" facs="tcp:66367:92"/>All about the Palace was written good Sentences, to put the Courtiers in mind of their du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty: And it was pleaſant enough to ſee his Officers and Courtiers joyn together, with Books in their hands, making at leaſt as if they ſaid their Prayers: and this ſhew of Devotion was abſolutely neceſſary for any man that meant to make his Fortune; and by the neglect of it, the Count <hi>Salazar,</hi> that had more Wit than Cunning or Devotion, had like ſeveral times to loſe his favour. One day, as he was coming into the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lace, he cry'd to the Guard at the door, <hi>Deo Gratias,</hi> which is uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally ſaid to the Porter of a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent: and being in the Privy Chamber another time, where there was a Gentleman who was to raiſe a Troop of Horſe: <hi>Sir,</hi> ſaid the Count, <hi>without doubt you
<pb n="179" facs="tcp:66367:92"/>will have your Commiſſion, if you are but well verſed in the Divine Service.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Arch-Duke had chid him for it ſeveral times, but he could not hold for his life; and find<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a Colonel that was turning over his Prayer-book, he ask'd him what is Trump to day? in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of asking what was the Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice of the day; which ſo incen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the good Prince, that he forbid <hi>Salazar</hi> the Court.</p>
            <p>This pleaſed the <hi>Spaniards</hi> ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry well; but the <hi>Flemmings,</hi> who are the better Chriſtians, cared not for ſo much ſhew and Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony. But this being the Face of the Court, made it the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pereſt place for <hi>Joſebeth</hi> to own her Converſion in. The Arch-Duke himſelf deſired to be her Godfather, which made all the Court talk of nothing but the
<pb n="180" facs="tcp:66367:93"/>Divine Grace; nay, at laſt they attributed her Converſion to the Piety and Prayers of the Arch-Duke.</p>
            <p>The Arch-Biſhop took care to have her inſtructed in the Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of Religion; but there hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened a diſpute betwixt him, and Seignior <hi>Roſetti,</hi> his Holineſs Internunce, that then reſided at <hi>Bruſſels;</hi> for he pretended, as re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſenting the Pope, to whom on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly it belong'd to open the Doors of the Church, that <hi>Joſebeth</hi> ought not to be Baptized, till ſhe had appeared before him. To pleaſe all Sides, the Arch-Biſhop, who had as much Civility as Knowledge and Piety, gave or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der that <hi>Joſebeth</hi> ſhould wait on the Internunce ſome days before her Baptiſm.</p>
            <p>At laſt, when the day for the Solemnity was come, they ſet up
<pb n="181" facs="tcp:66367:93"/>a Tribunal for the Arch-Biſhop without the Porch of the Church; and when he was ſet upon it, in his Pontifical Habits, <hi>Joſebeth</hi> was brought out of a Houſe hard by, to go to him. She was dreſſed all in White, and a Gare on her Head of the ſame colour. The Count of <hi>Swartzembourg,</hi> High-Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berlain to the Arch-Duke, led her by one hand, and the Counteſs of <hi>Boſſu,</hi> called by ſome, Dutcheſs of <hi>Guiſe,</hi> by the other. She appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſo lovely, that the Ladies of <hi>Bruſſels</hi> began to be allarmed with her Beauty; but her Counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance eaſed them again, for there appeared ſo much diſcreti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and modeſty, that they hoped ſhe would not go about to take away any of their Subjects. She kneeled before the Prelate, and having anſwered ſeveral Queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons he put to her, the Arch-Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop
<pb n="182" facs="tcp:66367:94"/>of <hi>Malines</hi> lead her into the Church, which till then had the Door ſhut. Then ſhe was over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyed to ſee her ſelf admitted there, and was perfectly ſatisfied, when ſhe ſaw the Arch-Duke ready to do her ſuch an honour, who na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med her at the Font, for himſelf and Madam <hi>de Boſſu, Maria Leo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poldina. Solomoune</hi> was Bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed at the ſame time, and <hi>Ville<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neufe</hi> would needs be Godfather.</p>
            <p>This Ceremony being over, <hi>Villeneufe,</hi> who foreſaw that <hi>Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſebeth</hi>'s beauty would quickly bring him a great many Rivals, begg'd leave of <hi>Joſebeth,</hi> and the Arch-Duke, that the Arch-Biſhop of <hi>Malines</hi> might finiſh his Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licity, which was performed with an Univerſal Joy, all the Court e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteeming <hi>Villeneufe</hi> very worthy of ſo extraordinary a Woman.</p>
            <p>He was uſed with extraordinary
<pb n="183" facs="tcp:66367:94"/>kindneſs by the Arch-Duke, but however deſired to return into his own Country, bearing with him Marks of the Duke's bounty, and a great Reputation of Virtue. By the means of his Friends, he made Intereſt enough to obtain a ſmall Government on the Fron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiers of <hi>France,</hi> where he taſted all thoſe ſingular joys that ſpring from a reciprocal affection.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:66367:95"/>
            <div n="books" type="part">
               <head>Books Printed for, and ſold by <hi>Richard Ton<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi> at <hi>Grays-Inn-Gate.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THe <hi>Courtiers Calling;</hi> ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the ways of making a Fortune, and the Art of living at Court. By a Perſon of Honour. Price 1 <abbr>
                     <hi>s.</hi>
                  </abbr> 6 <abbr>
                     <hi>d.</hi>
                  </abbr>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Portugal Hiſtory,</hi> or a Rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Troubles that happen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the Court of <hi>Portugal</hi> in the Years 1667. and 1668. In which is to be ſeen that great Tranſacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Renunciation of the Crown by <hi>Alphonſo</hi> the Sixth, the Diſſolution of his Marriage with the Princeſs <hi>Maria Frances Iſabella</hi> of <hi>Savoy;</hi> the Marriage of the ſame Princeſs to his Brother the Prince <hi>Don Pedro,</hi> now Regent of the Realm of <hi>Portugal,</hi> and the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons alledged at <hi>Rome</hi> for the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpenſation
<pb facs="tcp:66367:95"/>thereof. By <hi>S. P.</hi> Eſq; Price bound 3 <abbr>
                     <hi>s.</hi>
                  </abbr>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Art of making Love,</hi> or a Guide for Ladies and Gentlemen in the Affairs of Love. Price 1 <abbr>
                     <hi>s.</hi>
                  </abbr>
               </p>
               <p>A Treatiſe concerning Statutes, or Acts of Parliament, and the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition thereof. By Sir <hi>Charles Hatton,</hi> late Lord Chancellour of <hi>England.</hi> Price 1 <abbr>
                     <hi>s.</hi>
                  </abbr>
               </p>
               <p>The Life of the Valiant and Learned Sir <hi>Walter Raleigh,</hi> Knight, with his Tryal at <hi>Wincheſter,</hi> in <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctavo.</hi> Price 2 <abbr>
                     <hi>s.</hi>
                  </abbr> 6 <abbr>
                     <hi>d.</hi>
                  </abbr>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Marches</hi> Actions for Slander and Arbitrament; and alſo certain Queries, with the Books cited <hi>Pro</hi> and <hi>Con;</hi> very uſeful for Students in Law. By <hi>J. M.</hi> of <hi>Grays-Inne,</hi> Barriſter. Price 3 <abbr>
                     <hi>s.</hi>
                  </abbr>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reports,</hi> or new Caſes, taken in the 15, 16, 17, and 18. Years of King <hi>Charles</hi> the Firſt. By J. <hi>March</hi> of <hi>Grays-Inne,</hi> Barriſter. Price 3 <abbr>
                     <hi>s.</hi>
                  </abbr> 6 <abbr>d.</abbr>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:66367:96"/>
               <p>Tranſactions in <hi>Chancery,</hi> both by Practice and Preſidents, with the Fees thereunto belonging, and alſo Special Orders in ordinary Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes. By <hi>William Tothill,</hi> late one of the <hi>Six Clerks.</hi> Price 1 <abbr>
                     <hi>s.</hi>
                  </abbr> 6 <abbr>
                     <hi>d.</hi>
                  </abbr>
               </p>
               <p>Pleas of the Crown; being a brief account of whatſoever can be found relating to that Subject. Price bound 2 <abbr>
                     <hi>s.</hi>
                  </abbr> 6 <abbr>
                     <hi>d.</hi>
                  </abbr>
               </p>
               <p>Mr. <hi>Rimer</hi>'s Examination of the Plays of <hi>Rollo</hi> Duke of <hi>Normandy,</hi> the <hi>King, and no King,</hi> and the <hi>Maids Tragedy,</hi> in a Letter to <hi>Fleet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wood Sheppard,</hi> Eſq; Price 1 <abbr>
                     <hi>s.</hi>
                  </abbr> 6 <abbr>
                     <hi>d.</hi>
                  </abbr>
               </p>
               <p>An Hiſtorical Diſcourſe of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liaments, in their Original before the Conqueſt, and continuance ſince; together with the Original, growth, and continuance of theſe Courts following, <hi>(viz.)</hi> the <hi>High Court of Chancery, Kings Bench, Common Pleas, Exchequer, Dutchy,</hi> and other Inferiour Courts. Price 1 <abbr>
                     <hi>s.</hi>
                  </abbr>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:66367:96"/>
               <p>The <hi>Heroine Muſqueteer,</hi> or the <hi>Female Warrier,</hi> in four Parts; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining many true and delightful Adventures of a <hi>French</hi> Lady, in the late Campagnes of 1676. and 1677. newly Printed. Price bound 3 <abbr>
                     <hi>s.</hi>
                  </abbr>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="plays" type="part">
               <head>Plays Printed for <hi>Rich. Tonſon.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Don Carlos,</hi> Prince of <hi>Spain,</hi> a Tragedy: the ſecond Edition; act<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed at the Dukes Theatre. Price 1 <abbr>
                     <hi>s.</hi>
                  </abbr>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Titus</hi> and <hi>Berenice,</hi> a Tragedy; with a Farce called, <hi>The Cheats of Scapin:</hi> acted at the Dukes Thea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tre. Price 1 <abbr>
                     <hi>s.</hi>
                  </abbr>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Friendſhip in Faſhion:</hi> A Come<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, as it is acted at the Dukes Theatre. Price 1 <abbr>
                     <hi>s.</hi>
                  </abbr> All three writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten by <hi>Tho. Otway.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anthony</hi> and <hi>Cleopatra:</hi> A Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gedy written by Sir <hi>Charles Sidley,</hi> Baronet, acted at the Dukes Thea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tre. Price 1 <abbr>
                     <hi>s.</hi>
                  </abbr>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:66367:97"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Circe:</hi> A Tragedy, by <hi>Charles Davenant, L. L. D.</hi> Price 1 <abbr>
                     <hi>s.</hi>
                  </abbr> act<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed at the Dukes Theatre.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Cytherea,</hi> or the <hi>Enamouring Gir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle:</hi> A Comedy written by <hi>John Smith,</hi> Gent. Price 1 <abbr>
                     <hi>s.</hi>
                  </abbr>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Siege</hi> of <hi>Babylon:</hi> A Trage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, by <hi>Samuel Pordage,</hi> Eſq; as it is acted at the Dukes Theatre. Price 1 <abbr>
                     <hi>s.</hi>
                  </abbr>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Edgar,</hi> or the <hi>Engliſh Monarch:</hi> A Tragedy, written by <hi>Tho. Rimer</hi> of <hi>Grays-Inne,</hi> Eſq; Price 1 <abbr>
                     <hi>s.</hi>
                  </abbr>
               </p>
               <p>Sir <hi>Patient Fancy:</hi> A Comedy acted at the Dukes Theatre, and written by the Author of the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver.</hi> Price 1 <abbr>
                     <hi>s.</hi>
                  </abbr>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Brutus</hi> of <hi>Alba,</hi> or the <hi>Enchant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Lovers:</hi> A Tragedy acted at the Dukes Theatre, written by <hi>N. Tate.</hi> Price 1 <abbr>
                     <hi>s.</hi>
                  </abbr>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The Counterfeits:</hi> A Comedy as it is acted at the Dukes Theatre. Price 1 <abbr>
                     <hi>s.</hi>
                  </abbr>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:66367:97"/>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
